<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Herm'ælogium or, an essay at the rationality of the art of speaking. As a supplement to Lillie's grammer, philosophically, mythologically, &amp; emblematically offered by B.J.</title>
            <author>Jones, Bassett.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2122_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210164</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868988</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868988</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121348</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87625)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121348)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 242:E2122[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Herm'ælogium or, an essay at the rationality of the art of speaking. As a supplement to Lillie's grammer, philosophically, mythologically, &amp; emblematically offered by B.J.</title>
                  <author>Jones, Bassett.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 94+ p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for T. Fasset, in St. Dunstans-Church-yard in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement leaf and errata leaf proceed text.</note>
                  <note>Thomason copy cut off at p. 94.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Au:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Latin language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Herm'aelogium; OR, AN ESSAY At the rationality of the Art of SPEAKING.</p>
            <p>As a <hi>Supplement</hi> to <hi>Lillie</hi>'s Grammer, <hi>PHILOSOPHICALLY, MYTHOLOGICALLY,</hi> &amp; <hi>EMBLEMATICALLY</hi> Offered by <hi>B. J.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>In rational knowledges to depart from the received partitions, is no diſallowing of the ſame.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>L.</hi> Veru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam <hi>in his Advancement of Learning,</hi> p. <hi>330.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>T. Paſſet,</hi> in St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans-Church-yard</hi> in Fleet-ſtreet, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <p>THE Book analogizing words with things (particularly with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s intrinſecal principles of things) is divided into four parts. Whereof,</p>
            <list>
               <item>The firſt, under three Heads or Chapters, ſpecifieth the analogie
<list>
                     <label>Of</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>The word of Being or Noune Subſtantive</item>
                           <item>The word of Motionor Verb</item>
                           <item>The word of Quality or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <label>with</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Matter.</item>
                           <item>Form.</item>
                           <item>Privation.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>to fol. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121348:3"/>
               <item>The ſecond part, ſubdivided into five Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſheweth the variations and affections of the ſaid word of Being, both in its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominative Entity, and caſual qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>to fol. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The third, under the ſame number of Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſheweth the variations and affections of the word of Motion, <hi>to fol. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The fourth tranſiently examineth the ſtate of the four undeclined Parts of Speech, with their concomitant Mutes. And laſtly of the Pronoune, with the Arts therefrom proceedings, <hi>to fol. 73</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Whereunto be added the Philoſophical and Pedagogical uſes of the whole; with Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems of the ſame Mythologiz'd.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:3"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S ſome moneths ſithence (Reader) I was, among my ſelect companions, engaged in a diſcourſe relating to the Grammatical part of <hi>THE ADVANCEMENT OF LEARNING,</hi> penn'd by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouned <hi>Vicecount</hi> of St. <hi>Albans,</hi> I caſually fell upon this fanſie: Which I profeſs to have publiſhed out of no deſign to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, but a deſire to advance the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory way now in uſe, in ſome degree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that more proſperous State menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned<note n="*" place="margin">In Preface to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, fol. 5.</note> by his ſaid Lordſhip, <q>wherein the mind may practice her own power upon the nature of things.</q> And therefore have I entituled it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>i. e.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb facs="tcp:121348:4"/>Taking the ſighing Adverb for an actuated wiſh, and the God of Speech for the Art of Speaking.</p>
            <p>I ſay Art as obſerving the Creatures to be ſo far verbigerant as is requiſite both to the preſervation and promulgation of their kind, and the paucity of words in uſe not only among the Indians, but even that Nation whoſe language is recorded to us as moſt venerable, to evince that <hi>Man</hi> at firſt did not herein excell otherwiſe than as a diſtinction between ſpecifical ſound rude<note n="*" place="margin">Part 4. c. 1.</note> and conformed may eaſily inform us.</p>
            <p>But to what this conformity might be moſt naturally fanſied: how,<note place="margin">(a)</note> why and when graduated to that<note n="*" place="margin">Part 2. c 5. &amp; part 4. c. 2.</note> ſeptuple excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency we now find it in, I thought worthy of enquiry. Since that the Hebrew ſhould be either to all ſpeeches confounded, or that language whence the reſt ſhould be derived; ſaving the implicit belief I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfully owe to the Aſſertors, I find not ſo much as the reaſon either of diſcord or Symphonie. As for inſtance: Admit I granted that the Latine <hi>Cauis</hi> were deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Greeks; what were this to the Dog of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Houndt</hi> of Almayne; or either to <hi>KELEB</hi> of the Hebrew's?</p>
            <p>Moreover I find, that beſides the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility
<pb facs="tcp:121348:4"/>of reconciling the<note n="*" place="margin">Part. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Idioms, even in the reſpective refinement of the languages, not only the Northern and Southern people have run a contray courſe (the one multiplying Conſonants as learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly as the other endeavour to baulk them) But even the neighbour <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> the one expreſſing the Caſe of the Noun both by Article and Terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the other uſually couching the Article under the Termination. It being their deſign aſwell to expreſs much matter with little vocality, as to have ſeveral vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calities for the ſame matter or ſenſe.</p>
            <p>And I find laſtly that the <hi>Orthoaepia</hi> of that very language is not in all Countries the ſame; the <hi>Scio, folo, genus</hi> &amp;c. of the <hi>German</hi> being by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> rejected, the two firſt as a <hi>Plateaſmus;</hi> and the laſt as ſounding too much of aſperity; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> chooſing to pronounce the <hi>[G]</hi> ſo placed, like an <hi>[I]</hi> conſonant; which again the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> do reject; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing it rather like an <hi>[Sb]</hi> the <hi>[I]</hi> conſonant ſounding with them, and the <hi>Germans,</hi> much as with the <hi>Greeks;</hi> ſo that they account the <hi>Engliſh</hi> vocal ſound thereof as a <hi>Jotaciſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>REASON</hi> is one, ſo is it obſervable that the expreſſion thereof in
<pb facs="tcp:121348:5"/>and by man is in all Countries <hi>(quae Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon)</hi> the ſame; In that the Nations, differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vocality according to the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the reſpective climes they live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, do nevertheleſs in point of Syntaxe agree as one; thereby alſo manifeſting the product of words to be more from nature; as of Sentences from Reaſon; diſtinguiſh'd nevertheleſs but as ſo many gradual ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">See the wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> ch. 7. v. 15. &amp; 16.</note> 
               <hi>NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RING NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE;</hi> by the firſt underſtanding thoſe ſecret emanations of rude Nature which the Philoſophers of old called <hi>Chance;</hi> and by the ſecond that cultivated nature in its ſeveral uſes, through the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted. Arche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> log. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Scholaſtick ſtate of mans life, known by name of Diſcipline, Science, or Art; and now going under the general term of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy; or, to ſpeak ſtrictly, The Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophic of Grammer: for ſo, by Mr. <hi>Watts,</hi> do I find his ſaid Lordſhip interpreted.</p>
            <q>
               <p>We will (ſaith he)<note n="*" place="margin">In ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of learning, <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 260.</note> divide Grammer into two ſorts; whereof the one is lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, the other Philoſophical; the one is meerly applyed to languages that they may be the more ſpeedily learned, or more correctedly and purely ſpoken; the other in a ſort doth miniſter, and is ſubſervient to Philoſophie.</p>
               <p>In this latter part which is Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,
<pb facs="tcp:121348:5"/>we find that <hi>Caeſar</hi> writ Books <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Analogia;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Suet. in Jul.</note> and its a queſtion whether thoſe books handled this Philoſophical Grammer whereof we ſpeak? Our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is that there was not any high and ſubtile matter in them; but only that they deliver'd precepts of a pure and perfect ſpeech, not depraved by popular cuſtom, nor corrupted and polluted by over-cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious affection; in which kind <hi>Caeſar</hi> excell'd.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding admoniſhed by ſuch a work we have conceived and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in our mind a kind of Grammer, that may diligently enquire not the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of words one with another; but the analogie between words and things, or reaſon.—</p>
            </q>
            <p>On which words to quibble by queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning how an analogie can be underſtood otherwiſe than as ſubordinate to its Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern? And whether it doth not follow that <hi>Caeſars</hi> deſign alſo was to Analogize words with things or reaſon: I ſhould think almoſt as great a piece of incivility as is recorded of<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>H. L.</hi> his reign of K. <hi>Charles. p.</hi> 62.</note> that Doctor who was not aſhamed ſo to diſport himſelf with the brain-pan.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſhall ſilently trace his Lordſhip to the next page, where he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively
<pb facs="tcp:121348:6"/>ſets down the literary Grammer as a Deficient. Thereby manifeſting his former diviſion meant <hi>reſpectu ſtatus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionis;</hi> as a child is diſtinguiſhable from a man. And ſo I conceive his divided ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion receptible, as if he had continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſaid; There is a ſort of Grammer [ſuch as <hi>Lilie</hi>'s, &amp;c.] compos'd on the meer ſcore of Authority; no way prying into the reaſons thoſe Authors had for their ſo ſpeaking; As <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Books <hi>De Analogiâ</hi> did; and our ſelf thereby ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh'd have conceived and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our mind how to do.</p>
            <p>Which conception or intendment is my ſecurity, that neither thoſe writings of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> nor of any elſe<note n="*" place="margin">The here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten quoted Tract of <hi>Sealiger, De cauſis Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua Latinae,</hi> mainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy of that language more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly as it floweth from the <hi>Greek.</hi>
               </note> preciſely on this Subject are extant. Being confident that if any ſince had writ thereon it had been of publick uſe; as ſo tending to a recovery of the loſt rationality of <hi>Latine</hi> Syntax, now taught by meer obſervation; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding an expreſſion congruous only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its ſo read in <hi>Cicero, Terence, Virgil</hi> or <hi>Ovid.</hi> As if the knowledge of things by accidents were equally certain to that which cometh by their cauſes; and that notions entring through the doore of the underſtanding come no better prepared for retention, then do ſuch as like meer ſounds
<pb facs="tcp:121348:6"/>are only thruſt in at the ear-windores.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhips deſign in his propos'd Treatiſe of the divers properties of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; <q>That ſhould ſhew in what point every particular language did excel, and in what point it was deficient; that tongues might be inrich'd and perfected by mutual entertraffique one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo that a pattern might be drawn for the true expreſſion of the inward ſenſe of the mind from every part which is excellent in every language; inſomuch that obſervable conjectures might be taken touching the natural diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of People and Nations even from their Languages.</q>— I pretend to no ſuch perfection in language, as to engage therein further then as the diverſity of Idioms ſhall invite me to their examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in purſuance only of my firſt declar'd intendment.</p>
            <p>Wherein ſo worthy a pattern would have fortified the ſedulity of my imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had his Lordſhip been pleas'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what courſe either his Excellency took or himſelf deſigned for the ſtating of that Analogie, which, at this largeneſs, the reaſons<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> in my addreſs to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</note> hereafter manifeſted invite me to ſelect from <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> with hope only that, in an age wherein the wildeſt
<pb facs="tcp:121348:7"/>conceipts even of the tranſcendent entity do find acceptance, I need not deſpair of pardon; If by reducing the received parts of Speech to <hi>BEING, MOTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON</hi> and <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALITY,</hi> as their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples analogical to his<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt. 1. Phyſ c. 6. text, 42.</note> 
               <hi>MATTER, FORM,</hi> and <hi>PRIVATION,</hi> I do my Countryman but ſo much ſervice as (in his paſſage through the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Grammers) the eaſing of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory from the trouble of retaining more than hath been firſt digeſted by his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:7"/>
            <head>Theſe Books following are to be ſold by <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baſſet</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dunſtans-Church-yard</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe General Practice of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Orbis Miraculum,</hi> or the Temple of <hi>Solomon</hi> pourtrayed by Scripture-light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Samuel Lee,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Biſhopſgate, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirty Sermons preached at <hi>Milkſtreet, London;</hi> by <hi>Anthony Farindon,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baxters</hi> Treatiſe of Converſion.</p>
            <p>— Reformed Paſtor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hooles</hi> Grammer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Parnaſſi Puerperium,</hi> or ſome well-wiſhes to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, in the Tranſlation of <hi>Owen, Martial,</hi> and Sir <hi>Tho. Mores</hi> Epigrams, by <hi>Tho. Peck</hi> of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Temple, Gent.</p>
            <p>The Life and Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> from his Birth to his Burial, by <hi>Peter Heylin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Phyſical Diſcourſe touching the Nature and Effects of the Couragious paſſions, written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>Le chambre,</hi> and tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Principles of Chiromancy, written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>Le chambre,</hi> and tranſlated by a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>A Survey of the Law, containing Directions how to proſecute and defend perſonal actions uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally brought at Common Law, with the Judges opinions in ſeveral caſes; by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illiam Gliſſon</hi> and <hi>Anthony Gulſton,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſqs</abbr> and Bariſters at Law.</p>
            <p>The Exact Law-giver, containing the Chiefeſt grounds of the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Principles of Chriſtian Religion; by <hi>James Uſher</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:8"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. line <hi>ult</hi> for <hi>being in a ſort,</hi> read <hi>being a ſort.</hi> p. 12 l. 19. after the word <hi>right</hi> ſtop thus[;] p. 21. l. 20. blot out the firſt <hi>my.</hi> p. 40. l. 25. for <hi>as</hi> r. <hi>at.</hi> p. 44. l. 20. for <hi>[i]</hi> conceive[.] p. 54. l. 7. for whtch r. <hi>which.</hi> p. 58. l. <hi>ult.</hi> at the word <hi>action</hi> ſtop thus[.] p. 59. l. 1. blot out <hi>that.</hi> p. 65. l. 1. for <hi>quantites</hi> r. <hi>quantities.</hi> p. 66. l. 6. &amp; l. 30. for <hi>propoſition</hi> r. <hi>prepoſition. Ibid.</hi> l. 9. for <hi>minis</hi> r. <hi>nimis.</hi> p. 67. l. 4. for <hi>my ſcore</hi> r. <hi>my own ſcore.</hi> p. 68. l. <hi>ult.</hi> for <hi>fo</hi> r. <hi>for.</hi> p. 71. l. 25. for <hi>n</hi> r. <hi>In: Ibid.</hi> in marg. for <hi>argumenti</hi> r. <hi>argumentis.</hi> p. 93. l. 24. for <hi>quam</hi> read <hi>quum.</hi> p. 87. l. 4. blot out <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121348:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Herm'aelogium;</hi> The firſt PART.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Treating of the ſaid words in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral reſpective analogies. And firſt of the word of <hi>Being</hi> or noune ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive in its analogie to <hi>matter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſt place I offer thoſe words which ſerve to expreſs the Eſſence or Exiſtence of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whether in its innumerable parts or whole bulk, actions or paſſions; as properly called words of Being; In regard they are both the denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of entity, and alſo the <hi>baſis</hi> of motion; even as Matter is of Form. And as we cannot conceive Form without preſuppoſing Matter; no more may we, ſententiouſly, expreſs a motion without its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Being; all motion neceſſarily proceeding <hi>ab aliquo quieſcente.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo as matter doth <hi>appetere</hi> catch at or invade form in order to forms formed; So Being directeth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121348:9"/>Motion towards another Being<note n="*" place="margin">Quies priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ei. <hi>See</hi> Com. Magyr. l. r. c. 6.</note> qualified for the complement of a Sentence. The firſt being the material, and the laſt the formal or final cauſe of the motion.</p>
               <p>Wherefore alſo as in the one place it is <hi>terminus à quo,</hi> active, and therefore governing: It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that in the tother it be <hi>terminus ad quem fit motus;</hi> and conſequently <hi>(ſenſu receptitiae perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis)</hi> paſſive, and ſo governed.</p>
               <p>The ſame is hinted at by our <hi>LILLIE,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the queſtions <hi>WHO</hi> or <hi>WHAT?</hi> and <hi>WHOM</hi> or <hi>WHAT?</hi> The firſt as the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive caſe to, and the ſecond as the caſual word of the Verb; which laſt I hereafter diſtinguiſh by name of a word of Senſe, in regard that by its ſenſuality it compleateth this Phyloſophie of a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. To which neither the Verb imperſonal, its Latine <hi>ſuccedaneum</hi> the Gerund with the Verb of Being, nor the Infinitive Mood can be an excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. While the word or words mediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt, and immedately the ſecond, are, in ſenſe, as their nominative caſe; In that they are their material cauſe or <hi>baſis;</hi> and the third ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth no other then the eſſence<note n="*" place="margin">Part 3. cap 1.</note> ot indefinit Being of a Motion. Which the Greeks and Engliſh ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, while they denominate their Verbs by the Infinitve mood, as, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, To love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore our Author teacheth that when two <q>Verbs meet together, the latter ſhall be the Infinitve Mood.</q> That Mood ſo placed bearing the ſame ſignification with an eſſential word of ſenſe; as when placed before the Verb it doth of a word of Being; and ſerves either to govern or be Governed by the Verb accordingly.</p>
               <p>And becauſe it often doth this accompanyed; not only by words of the ſame ſort by way of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121348:9"/>appoſition, but by the Infinitive Mood and a word of Being; ſo anſwering both the queſtions, <hi>WHOM</hi> and <hi>WHAT:</hi> Our Author adds, that <hi>Aliquando ratio eſt verbo nominativus.</hi> Which <hi>aliquando</hi> I ſuppoſe he would have underſtood as a conditional <hi>ſemper.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Whenever you meet with any number of words without a Verb in a Mood other then the infinitive, know that they all can amount to no compleat ſentence; but only to ſuch a <hi>Ratio</hi> as may ſerve for a nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive caſe to the Verb. And the reaſon therefore is, that they ſignifie no more then one word of Being, as is evident even by the example he there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanceth out of <hi>Ovid:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Ingenuas didiciſſe fideliter artes</l>
                     <l>Emollit mores.—</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>All which, but for the emphaſis and verſe, (which are but as the ſecond intentions of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) might have been as fully expreſſed by one word of Being, as if he had ſaid <hi>Literatura emollit mores.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121348:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the word of Motion or Verb, in its ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie to Form.</head>
               <p>PRoceeding ſecondly to motion,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its, paſſage, I obſerve it twofold, <hi>viz.</hi> either going from, or elſe coming towards the firſt ſententiouſly expreſſed Being: as, I love, or I am loved. Yet <hi>(tranſpoſitis terminis)</hi> this duplicity will appear to be but ſo many gradual expreſſions of one and the ſame motion. As when I ſay, <hi>JOHN LOVETH JOAN,</hi> I thereby but only expreſs the action of love as barely proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>John</hi> towards <hi>Joan;</hi> and ſo a Cat may look upon a King. But if I ſay <hi>JOAN IS LOVED BY JOHN,</hi> I then not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs as much, but alſo manifeſt the energie of <hi>Johns</hi> love-motion to be ſuch, as that <hi>Joan</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in paſſionately concern'd.</p>
               <p>And hence (with ſubmiſſion to my more learned Readers) I conceive the antients came todiſtinguiſh the one by name of a Verb paſſive, from that other of an active. And particularly the Latins (with whom this voice is moſt Idiomatical) to form the paſſive from the active by the only addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the letter <hi>[R].</hi> And that <hi>Magyrus</hi> alſo in his<note n="*" place="margin">lib. 1. c. 4.</note> Phyſiologie comes to declare that <hi>Motus in duobus conſiſtit</hi> (he doth not ſay <hi>duo motus</hi>) <hi>in agente</hi> ſcil. <hi>&amp; Patiente.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thereby, however, excluding our Authors Neuter-paſſives, Common and Deponents; as products of a vain attempt of reconciling the Latine and Engliſh Idioms, not conſidering how
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121348:10"/>the firſt denominate their Verbs <hi>à cauſâ cauſae,</hi> and the laſt <hi>à cauſâ cauſati.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which once obſerved, it will be evident that the Romans were never<note n="*" place="margin">To multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply diviſions to their low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity is an errour in Science. <hi>L. Vetu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ibid.</note> guilty of troubling us with any ſuch ſubdiviſion. As for inſtance: <hi>Vapulo</hi> and <hi>Exulo</hi> muſt with them needs be Verbs active: It being their Philoſophie that <hi>Nemo laeditur niſi à ſcipſo.</hi> And ſo muſt <hi>Precor</hi> and <hi>Meditor</hi> be paſſives, ſince it was as well their Theologie that
<q>— Timor primos fecit in orbe Deos.</q> 
                  <hi>Loquor</hi> likewiſe and <hi>Argumentor,</hi> ſtrictly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, being when we ſpeak or argue the ſenſe of others. Beſides that, admitting of a gradation, it were not Scholaſtick to multiply its comparative Arithmetick beyond a third,<note place="margin">(a)</note> (where I ſtate the Verb imperſonal) as in the following Chapter is expreſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121348:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the word of Quality, or Noun-Adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, in its analogie to Privati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUR Author telling us that the coherence of the former word with its nominative caſe is in reſpect of number and perſon:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I reſerve its ſaid ſuperlative gradation, as more properly explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able among thoſe and the variations of the whole three. The laſt whereof I now offer as the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Privation, or (in corporeal naturalities) Proportion; both being here underſtood in order to perfection. By which as we attain to the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of great and little as a quantity; ſo of good and evil as a quality; and by it come we to the uſeful knowledge of quantitative qualities, to make them alſo adjectible to Beings.</p>
               <p>For, although naturally they admit not of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, the leaſt drop being logically as much water as is the whole Sea; Yet being coacervated, as they take up the rooms of great and little, two being more then one, and three then two, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they become convertible with good and evil; the biggeſt (as we uſe to ſay, <hi>caeteris paribus</hi>) being alwayes the beſt.</p>
               <p>And ſithence we find dilatation and good to be euqally appetible by all Beings, the converſion cannot be improper.<note place="margin">As is partly demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by a Cyphon.</note> Wherefore we call a great houſe a good houſe; and ſo do we complement My very good Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which nevertheleſs to wreſt too much to a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121348:11"/>Political ſenſe, were to make contentment no other than a lazie patience. Ot if to a Theological, to be forced with that otherwiſe thrice learned<note n="*" place="margin">Campanel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la in Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſmo trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phato.</note> Dominican, ſometimes of my acquaintance in <hi>PARIS,</hi> to defend covetouſneſs to be no ſin; and conſequently, with ſome Philoſophers of the Neotericks, be ſeduced, practically, to confound <hi>Honeſtum</hi> with <hi>Utile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore its obſervable that both quantity and quality become diſtinguiſhers of good and evil only mediately. The one by coacervation, as aforeſaid; and the other by ſeparation: <hi>Unum, verum, bonum, ens, quatenus ens,</hi> being alwaies the ſame.</p>
               <p>But if we apply an Entity or Being to a praeterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural uſe,<note place="margin">Amygdalae amarae noxiae vulpibus. <hi>I. Mart. Met. ſect.</hi> 6.</note> then ſhall we find (as was retorted by the Hollander) that Engliſh Ale is no better to thatch houſen, then is Dutch butter to ſtop Ovens.</p>
               <p>Or otherwiſe, if we contemplate ſeveral beings of the ſame kind or ſort, by the privation of ſome particle of perfection in the one, we learn to value the excellency of the other. And in caſe there be two beings herein compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible; there the ſenſes immediately ſummon a Court of Survey; where opinion ſitting as Judge decides the controverſie by the line or meaſure of compariſon. Which ſubjects all qualities under ſo variable a conſtruction: it being impoſſible that all Beings ſhould be affected to one and the ſame Quality, more than all Qualities may be ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally adjectible to one Being. Or to inſtance that Elementary Being which is permanent in its affection towards a ſingle Quality or Being ſo qualified. Since as the temperament alters, ſo muſt the Judgement; and Affection being to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121348:12"/>Judgement, as the Cauſe to the Effect: hence neceſſarily proceed both the<note n="*" place="margin">I meddle not with the ſupernal allyance of the ſtars. Only as my Vernacular Idiome renders it, <hi>Kyfanian a G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rthani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi>
                  </note> Sympathy and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy of the Univerſe.</p>
               <p>This we may read moſt handſomly exemplified in the obſervations left us by<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gic.</note> 
                  <hi>Strada</hi> on the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults of the Council held at <hi>Madrid</hi> before the Expedition which the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> thereupon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook for the Netherlands. To which he adds, <q>That every man while he votes for the publike, votes for himſelf. And the vote (ſaith he in Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton's</hi> language) which nature ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orts, we thinK we give to the cauſe, when, indeed, we do it to our own humor.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs we find this wiſe Nature, in order to the preſervation of it ſelf in its reſpective In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals, to have ſtamped certain characters of general reception on Good and Evil; even as by a number of myſterious lines on the face, the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are promoted in order to beauty: as we may be more at large ſatisfied concerning the one by the Mathematicks, as of the other among the Ethicks.</p>
               <p>My preſent part being only by this difficulty to inſtance how expedite it was that the degrees of compariſon ſhould be carv'd exactly anſwerable to the Hermetical Phyloſophie of Vertue; which is, To be multiplyed in the ſecond, and compleated in the third. That number being worthily magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Antients as moſt perfect, in regard it is uncapable of an equal diviſion;<note place="margin">(a)</note> and ſo remains of Infinitneſs the neareſt repreſentative imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And this the French idiome confirms by its expreſſion of moſt by thrice: as, <hi>Grand, Plus grand, trois grand.</hi> Great, Greater, Greateſt. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnus, Major, Maximus:</hi> The reſt, in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, having for the moſt part their ſuperlative
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121348:12"/>in <hi>[iſſimus]</hi> as <hi>faelix faeliciſſimus:</hi> Excepting ſuch as are called <hi>Anomola</hi> or irregular; or whoſe riſe is mentioned affectedly: as, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lior</hi> for <hi>Mollior,</hi> or <hi>Maximus</hi> for <hi>Maximè optatus.</hi> To compare by <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>maximè</hi> being proper only to words ending with a yowel before [us] In regard [be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the too much overture of concurrent vowels is in ſome ſort abhorred by all languages] the regular compariſon renders ſuch ſcarce com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible by any <hi>Latine</hi> verſe, except the Lyric: And therefore do the <hi>Romans</hi> compare them by their Adverbs; much as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> more and moſt.</p>
               <p>But to conclude. As Privation became known by contemplation of want, the high way to nothing: So Quality can, Grammatically, ſignifie nothing, until it be adjected to that Being whereof it ſhew's the quality; as to ſay, A fair woman, a large hawk, &amp;c. and therefore is the Adjective in what degree ſoever plac'd to agree with its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive in Gender, Caſe and Number, as affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which by it are occaſionally varyed as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121348:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Herm'aelogium.</hi> The Second Part.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Shewing the Rational Variations or Affections of the Noun Subſtantive, whether in its Entitative denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſenſual caſuality. And firſt of its Articulation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O this word do belong firſt its articles: He, She, or It. The word <hi>Genus</hi> being here, as I with the ſame ſubmiſſion conceive, underſtood by the Latines in a mixt ſenſe; For if we look upon it Logically, it will appear to be rather <hi>Species generis</hi> than <hi>Genus.</hi> And if meerly Phyſically <hi>à generando:</hi> Then muſt we take it only as an article manifeſting the property of a Being in point of generation; that is, Whether it be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121348:13"/>male, female, or neither. The Engliſh underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it no further, whiles, until they be of years to propagate, they articulate the nobleſt of Creatures by this neither or <hi>neuter</hi> gender, as when they ſay: It's a pretty Girl or Boy.</p>
               <p>Whereas the <hi>Latins</hi> uſe it not only to diſtinguiſh the Sex, but alſo the active and paſſive qualities of Beings in point of uſe, as; <hi>Hic liber, haec Pila.</hi> The book being look'd upon as an agent by which we are inſtructed, and the Ball as a patient by the toſſing whereof we are recreated. Which yet I find to hold moſt in the articulation of ſuch words as be radically <hi>Latine;</hi> ſuch as derive from the <hi>Greek</hi> being articulated commonly as moſt conſonant with their terminations. So, <hi>Hic lapis, Haec petra.</hi> Which I rather take with<note n="*" place="margin">De cauſ. ling. lat. l. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Scaliger</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, than with the Antients from <hi>pedem laeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> and <hi>quià teratur pedibus;</hi> or from any experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their growth found out by the Neote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rics.</p>
               <p>Yet its obſervable that ſuch <hi>Greek</hi> words as be Latiniz'd only <hi>quoad ſonum</hi> do ſometimetimes herein outſtretch our uſe of the Being, by a<note n="*" place="margin">Enallage generis.</note> trope which the <hi>Latines</hi> declare themſelves not a little enamour'd with whiles not only the repeſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of ſometimes living perſonages, as <hi>Statua;</hi> but ſuch dead being as be either actually or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentially but the containers [as the place and placed] of the living, are by them numbred among the feminines: as, <hi>Manus, Domus, Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So they articulate the names of all Cities, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſuch as ſo ſtrictly follow the names of their Founders, that their termination cannot properly be advanc'd to the feminin gender. And only theſe, being in a ſort of more remote tropical
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121348:14"/>feminines, do they articulate rather according to their termination; which may be a reaſon why <hi>Londinum</hi> may not be declin'd feminiely aſwell as <hi>Glycerium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Derivative Beings, whoſe names proceed from primitive <hi>Latine</hi> words, they decline according to the nature of that word whence the derivation proceedeth; and in caſe the derivative proceeds from more then one, they take the denomination <hi>à fortiori;</hi> whether that be a word of Being, or a word of Motion. For example, <hi>Fluvius</hi> if it had its denomination from the water or the fiſh it is ſuppos'd to contain, muſt have been articula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted femininly: But ſithence it is neither the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor the fiſh, but the fierce flowing that makes the <hi>Fluvius</hi> of the <hi>Latines</hi> [for they have their <hi>Rivi</hi> and <hi>Rivuli</hi> beſides] there it is known by the maſculine gender.</p>
               <p>And the denomination is right in regard that as every Spring doth not make a River, no more doth every River contain fiſh. As the River <hi>Dulais</hi> of <hi>Neath ultra</hi> in <hi>Glamorganſhire,</hi> which, until of late years ſome Trouts were caſt into it, contained no fiſh but Eels; whoſe univocal generation being uncertain, are therefore articulated doubtfully. Suppoſing always that I latinize them by the old name of <hi>Anguis,</hi> [Snakes and Adders being num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the <hi>Oviparia</hi>] and not <hi>Anguilla;</hi> for then I make it an <hi>Epicaen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame rule ſtandeth for Hermaphroditical creatures. And not unlike is that way of articula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they call common, as <hi>Hic &amp; Haec Canis.</hi> The main end we keep Dogs for being in order to our pleaſure of hunting them according to their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive kinds, to which ſince we do not find that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of ſex doth add any thing, they are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121348:14"/>properly articulated with caution only that we diſtinguiſh them from dead Being.</p>
               <p>As for our Authors Common of three, I obſerve that as proper only for the declenſion of Adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives; it being impoſſible a Being ſhould be living and dead at the ſame inſtant.</p>
               <p>Vegetives, in regard their multiplication is at a diſtance, are, when their termination invites it, content to be articulated neutrally: as,<note n="*" place="margin">Mas &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thium.</hi> Otherwiſe for the moſt part we read them promiſcuouſly ſpecified aſwell by the maſculine as feminine gender. The diſtinguiſhment of their ſex being a knowledge peculiar only to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians.</p>
               <p>So that I dare not induce a reaſon for our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſtrict muliebrity of <hi>Alnus, quia alatur amne.</hi> While I find <hi>amnis</hi> both maſculine and femininely declin'd. Neither can his firſt ſpecial Rule oblige me to it; whiles <hi>Pinus</hi> coming alſo within that verge, I find maſculinely, and (by Mr. <hi>Hollyoak's</hi> obſervation) aſwell feminiely declin'd.</p>
               <p>Wherefore where our Author ſaith, that <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellativa arborum erunt muliebria ut Alnus,</hi> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him as only telling me he never read it otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>But ſince its my preſent undertaking to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to reach the reaſon of the Ancients for what our Author delivers on the meer account of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: The uſe the Ancients made of that Tree being mainly for ſhipping; as appeareth not only by the authority of <hi>Pliny,</hi> but alſo that the <hi>Brittains</hi> do at this day call the Shipmaſt, although conſiſting of other timber, by name of that<note n="*" place="margin">Gỽernen y Llong.</note> tree; therefore were I not thereby neceſſitated to hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roclite it, I ſhould, after <hi>Plinie's</hi> example, take the Tree for the Ship that is thereof built, or at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121348:15"/>leaſt wiſe that by it is perfected, and ſo make it a tropical feminine, as <hi>Domus.</hi> And who knoweth but that in the infant refinement of the language it was ſo taken and declined, while Mr. <hi>Hollyoake</hi> derives it from the ſame root with <hi>Quercus?</hi> Since as<note n="*" place="margin">In Epiſt. dedicat.</note> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> well obſerves, <hi>Voces &amp; familiaris ſermo ſuas habent viciſſitudines; &amp; magis convenit inter linguas Gallicam &amp; Italorum, quâm Latinitati ſequioris aevi cum Ennianâ</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Caſes.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond variation of this word is according to the reſpective conditions it may ſerve in, whether Genitive, Dative, Accuſative, or Abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. The ſervice it doth Vocatively being barely Salutatorie; and Nominatively, either as appoſited to a word of its own ſort, or ſubjected only to its own motion. And therefore do I rather adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on this my own fancyed conditional definition of the Caſes, then comply with the learned <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligers à Cadendo,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as he<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. p. 183.</note> renders it; that extraction too much entrenching on the ſtate of this Caſe; whoſe ſaid imployment can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged no more cadent than for one hand to ſerve another.</p>
               <p>The ſervices it performs in its other conditions are firſt as it is governed by another word of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And ſo it ſerves the Engliſh man commonly Genitively: The houſe of his father, and the uſe of his friend ſounding to him alike. But with the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121348:15"/>
                  <hi>Roman</hi> the firſt bearing the ſenſe of a poſſeſſion, and the ſecond of an inſtrument; therefore that ſhall be govern'd Genitively, and this Ablatively; and that for reaſons in its motional governance ſpeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</p>
               <p>As for its Dative ſervice, I obſerve that either to Subſtantives compounded with ſuch Prepoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as our Author notes to bring the Verb ſo governing: as, <hi>Mihi praefectus, advocatus, contu.</hi> &amp;c. or elſe to a Being <hi>qua</hi> qualitative; as, <hi>urbi pater</hi> i. e. <hi>Patronus:</hi> The Engliſh to the Adjective ſubjecting it all one way, and in as many condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as do the <hi>Latins,</hi> which is in all the four: As,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Novitatis avida,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sis bonus tuis,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dives Nummis</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gnomon ſeptem pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des longus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Greedy of news.</item>
                     <item>Be good to thy own.</item>
                     <item>Rich in money.</item>
                     <item>A line ſeven foot loog.</item>
                  </list> Which laſt only ſoars up to the <hi>Latine</hi> rationality; the reſt carrying their ſigns before them; and ſo, in my opinion, may excuſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> man from the trouble of conning our Authors dilatations on this Rule. Sithence as we muſt neceſſarily know before we can compoſe; ſo doth the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what condition to place the goverened word in the <hi>Latine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And its obſervable that where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates it ſelf above the pitch of vulgarity, the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> as in diſdain of that pride, endeavours to ſoar higher: witneſs that Authority cited by our Author out of <hi>Columella: Fons latus pedibus tribus, altus triginta:</hi> Where the lateral meaſure governeth Ablatively, and the direct Accuſatively, by the ſame tacit reaſon as doth the Verb.</p>
               <p>In which Philoſophical Concordancie conſiſts
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121348:16"/>the main ſubtilty of the <hi>Roman</hi> language, <hi>viz.</hi> In ſubjecting this word in order to the concluſion of a ſentence, according to the reſpective inclinations of the motion. As;</p>
               <p>Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Genitively: And that to Verbs ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Poſſeſſion, Mercy, Memory, Enjoyments, or moſt things that belong to tryals or Barre-affairs. And the reaſon therefore will be obvious, if we but continue our obſervation of their forecited me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, as of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nominating, ſo of governing, <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum cauſam cauſae,</hi> and not <hi>couſati,</hi> as do the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A cuſtom which I ſuppoſe firſt grounded on a Metaphyſical conſideration: The Metaphyſicks ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the firſt as the more worthy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fitteſt for denomination and government. See <hi>jacob. Martin. in part. Metaphyſic. Sect.</hi> 7. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>But to come to our Authors inſtances, <hi>Miſerere mei,</hi> Have mercy of, or [as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by their prepoſitionally noted idiome more properly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it] upon me: We ſhall by the ſaid obſervation find it the ſame as to ſay, Let my miſer move your mercy to incline towards me. For by thoſe words we may obſerve my miſery to be the <hi>Cauſa cauſae,</hi> your mercy the <hi>Cauſa cauſati;</hi> and your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining of it towards me to be the <hi>Cauſatum.</hi> And ſo ſhall we diſcern How <hi>miſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re mei</hi> carries the ſame rationality of expreſſion as <hi>Patris</hi> or <hi>Paterna do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> For my miſery being come the cauſe of your mercy makes your mercy to be mine.</p>
               <p>I could illuſtrate this further, not only by the imitation of other languages; as of the <hi>French, Pittie du moi,</hi> &amp;c. but alſo by the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oman</hi> denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this motion or verb of Mercy from Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery: <hi>Miſereo, quaſi miſeriâ afflcior;</hi> and <hi>Miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdia, quaſi aegritudo cordis ex miſeriâ alterius.</hi> But
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121348:16"/>I rather chooſe yet to explain it by another of our Authors examples: <hi>Furti abſolutus eſt.</hi> Where I alſo find <hi>Furti</hi> governed Genitively. In regard that if the Priſoner had not firſt given ſome cauſe of ſuſpition, neither Jury nor Judge ſhould have ſate on him. Wherefore as the abſolution is the <hi>Cauſati,</hi> and ſo the priſoners own ſuſpicious demeanure is the <hi>Cauſa Cauſae:</hi> which proving but a ſuſpition, doth lead the Judge to the abſolution as of due be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſuſpected. And ſo doth <hi>Abſolve</hi> govern <hi>Furti</hi> Genitively, becauſe the ſuſpected having deſerved no other, hath entituled himſelf to the abſolution as his own. And by the like reaſon be all thoſe fore-hinted Verbs ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.</p>
               <p>And as poſſeſſion doth preſuppoſe acquiſition,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſo doth our Author in the next place ſubject it Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively; and that by ſuch Verbs as are acquiſitively poſited, which I mention by his his own word in regard he hath thereby ſaid all; the whole Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he after muſters up being rationally compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible under acquiſition. And that likewiſe by the fore-taught obſervance of the remoter cauſe. For ſo it comprehendeth loſs aſwell as profit; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence as there is no <hi>WHY</hi> without a <hi>WHERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE;</hi> ſo no man damnifieth another but in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his own advantage, more then it is poſſible one ſhould give what he hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p>As for Verbs moving in order to payments, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Negotiations, commands and obſequies, their end is ſufficiently expreſſed by the old Rithme,
<q>
                     <l>So ne do go, and ſome do runne,</l>
                     <l>But 'tis for money when all is done.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:121348:17"/>
               <p>And its obſervable that this acquiſitive inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Verb doth ſo badge its governed caſe, that not only Verbs compounded with the notes uſually prepoſited to the governance of other caſes do then require this; But alſo that we intelligibly can expreſs the word compleating their ſenſe by no other caſe, without the addition of a Prepoſition; which his fore-cited Lordſhip of <hi>Verulam</hi> notes for a<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid, fol. 262.</note> looſe, he might have ſaid pernicous, way of delivery.</p>
               <p>Its unlimited uſe (as by our Author inſtanced) rendring both this and the Genitive caſes of the Noun uſeleſs Sithence the ſenſe of this caſe becomes ſo expreſſible by Prepoſitions ſerving to the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative; as of the other by the Ablative: Excepting only when the Prepoſition <hi>tenus</hi> noteth poſſeſſion without deſired acquiſition; as <hi>Aurium tenus,</hi> it alſo handing a ſingular Ablative: as <hi>Pube tenus.</hi> The misfortune (as we ſay in <hi>Engliſh</hi>) being not all a caſe.</p>
               <p>However, that it doth not regulate when the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual word is to be expreſſed by a Prepoſition, and when according to the inclination or line of the Verb, I thought requiſite to note for a ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in Grammer, and ſuch as could ſcarce be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd without a preliminary examination How the infancy, ſtate and declination of the language did reſpectively uſe it.</p>
               <p>The firſt (having no books by me that inform) I muſt gueſs at from Mr. <hi>Robinſons</hi> (to our Author annexed) defective Heteroclites; which (leaving the redundant as enough for his <hi>Sors</hi> and <hi>Authorum placita</hi>) I ſuppoſe deſignedly ſo paſs'd by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finers, as a monument to poſterity what the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage formerly had been; that ſo their pains might be the more thank worthy. For did we not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121348:17"/>know that <hi>Carnu</hi> was once under that ſingl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation declined throughout our Authors ſix Caſes (excepting the Vocative, which no dead Being can ſtand in, becauſe uncapable of ſalute) and ſo no otherwiſe diſtinguiſhable than by Epithets and prepoſited notes:
<q>
                     <hi>Lucan's</hi> — Cornus tibi cura ſiniſtri.</q> Had been no elegant expreſſion at all; no more were our Authors <hi>Patris</hi> or <hi>Paterna domus</hi> a refined <hi>Latin</hi> phraſe; but for <hi>dumo</hi> or, as the modern have it, <hi>Caſa del Padre</hi> of the degenerate <hi>Italian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This evinceth that as much of the art of <hi>Latine</hi> Grammer was plac'd in the variation of the Nounes Termination according to (though ſeldom as manifold as) its caſes, and of them after the four inclinations or lines of the Verb; ſo the end in both was to heighten the language above the laid prepoſited vulgar way of ſpeaking. How far then the deſign fell ſhort in the projection becomes hence conſiderable.</p>
               <p>Wherein ere I proceed, I muſt remind my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how in the front of this tract I only promiſed an Eſſay at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ationality of Speech: If happily ſome more literate and ingenious might vouchſafe its foſtering to a perfect grandeur. And on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhall I here expoſe ſuch reaſons as at preſent to me occur dehortative to this intended baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The rather being thereto encouraged by the fore-cited Noble Lord<note n="*" place="margin">In mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> p. 1.</note> where he ſaith: <q>It is better to give a beginning to a thing that may once come to an end, than with an eternal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and ſtudy to be enwrapp'd in thoſe mazes which are endleſs.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then I obſerve that as the <hi>Euphonie</hi> of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121348:18"/>Southern Languages conſiſts in a ſmoothneſs of delivery,<note place="margin">See the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. f. l. 2.</note> ſo muſt the multiplicity of concurrrent Vowels aſwell as Conſonants be by them baulk'd as equally diſrelliſhing. Hence comes it that the <hi>French</hi> do often pronounce a fanſied Conſonant between; as when inſteed of <hi>Eſte il diſner?</hi> hath he dined? they ſay <hi>Ete til dine?</hi> and that the <hi>Roman</hi> Idiome doth interpoſe a Prepoſition; mine hoaſt with our Author ſo anſwering that <hi>Summâ cum humanitate tractavit hominem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That the ſaid lines are but <hi>Influx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Cauſae;</hi> and conſequently indicating rational rather than material governances. Wherefore I ſay <hi>Amo Virginem,</hi> but <hi>vado ad eam.</hi> And on this account do I ſuppoſe that <hi>Scaliger</hi> calls the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition by name of<note n="*" place="margin">Motum ad locum. <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pul.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. It being convenient that ſome expreſſed note ſhould hand a corporal motion, faculty or poſture both in its<note n="*" place="margin">Being or Eſſence. <hi>Eſſentia eſt principium motus</hi> ſaith <hi>I. Mart.</hi>
                  </note> beginning, end and ſpace between the word of Being and word of Sence.</p>
               <p>As when I ſay <hi>Lateo in ſepe.</hi> So denoting reſt in the Being.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curro è ſepe.</hi> Shewing the motions progreſs from it. Or</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Propero ad Sepem.</hi> Indicating its ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance towards it as its formal cauſe or word of ſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Cum omne corpus <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> aut movetur aut quieſcit: opus fuit aliquâ notâ quae <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,<note place="margin">Ibid. c. 157.</note> ſive eſſet inter duo extrema, inter quae motus fit: ſive in altero extremorum in quibus fit quies.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But (with due reverence to the memory of ſo renowned a Philoſopher) the moſt abſolute need
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121348:18"/>of the Prepoſition I find to be when I am to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the whole three joyntly; as ſaying <hi>Salio trans ſepem;</hi> ſo at once both ſuppoſing a reſt whence I take my leap; naming the hedge; and tending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a third place as the end of my motion. For theſe lines in their ſaid influx being no other than as imaginary Hierogliphicks cannot poſſibly indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſeveral ways at once.</p>
               <p>Elſe as one Caſe is prefer'd to another in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance; ſo ſhall we find the unuſher'd caſes to the Prepoſitionally noted ones wherever a material motion may be reduc'd to a lineal ſenſe: As when I ſay <hi>Dego Lutetiae;</hi> rejecting <hi>Apud Lutetiam</hi> as barre (I will not ſay barbarous) <hi>Latine.</hi> And yet I ſay <hi>Apud forum</hi> ſpeaking of ſome Market even in <hi>Paris.</hi> For, it's poſſible I may be at the market, and yet poſſeſs'd of nothing there ſaleable; therefore do I hand the condition of that Noune by the Prepoſition. But ſince I cannot properly be ſaid to be at the City without my implying my <hi>pro tempore</hi> poſſeſſion of a Being there, I condition thar rather after the circular line of the Verb, as when reſpecting the Inhabitants I do it after the oblique; my being there ſo aſwell ſuppoſing a benefit, were it but to the Tavern and Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor. Or, if my condition be mean, that I muſt have ſome way of acquiſition to ſubſiſt my ſaid being amongſt them. Wherefore I then ſay <hi>Pariſiis.</hi> As when I would intimate both the place and Inhabitants joyntly I expreſs my ſelf Genitively, ſaying <hi>Lutetiae Pariſiorum;</hi> that of the two being the moſt worthy caſual Poſition.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> hath a Rule that (baulking the abſurdity of teaching the <hi>Latine</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Idiome, which in this very particular confounds compleat with imperfect narratives) depends much
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121348:19"/>on the ſame Phyloſophy.<note place="margin">See his Grammar p. 76.</note> Saith he <q>[of] after a Verb tranſitive is alwayes expreſſed by the Prepoſition <hi>[de]</hi> as <hi>Loquor de Monarchia.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon is that the relation of the Monarchy being not abſolute, it falleth ſhort of a tranſitive; and therefore being comprehenſible by none other of the ſaid lines, the caſual word muſt be uſher'd by a Prepoſition.</p>
               <p>And ſo our Authors <hi>Mereor cum adverbiis:</hi> the deſert not reaching the whole man, the Adverb is uſed circumſtantially to expreſs how well or ill, much or little; which at moſt amounting but to a part, leaves the caſual word under the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p>Where its further obſervable that motions tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards fixt Beings have the circumſtance of their failing more elegantly expreſt by a note ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the ſenſe both of Adverb and Prepoſition; as <hi>Propè Templum, procul urbe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I finde the Prepoſition to be of uſe when ever the <hi>Cauſa propter quam</hi> of a motion is expreſſible;<note place="margin">Prepter do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> as to ſay, <hi>John</hi> loveth <hi>Joan</hi> for her dowrie. The line of the Verb's governance reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but <hi>a termino in terminum.</hi> And</p>
               <p>Fourthly, when the formal cauſe of a motion is alſo eſſicient; the ſaid lines as they indicate ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional rather than material governances; ſo do they the formality, &amp; not materiality or eſſence of the word of Senſe. And therefore ſaith our Author <hi>Baccharis prae ebrietate:</hi> and <hi>Terence, è Davo hoc a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>divi;</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>Davus</hi> told it me. And the ſame 'tis when the Active voyce of a Verb be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Paſſive; where inſtead of <hi>John</hi> loveth <hi>Joan,</hi> I ſay <hi>Joan</hi> is loved by <hi>John;</hi> he ſo becoming an efficient cauſe of her paſſion, as in the ſecond chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the firſt part of this diſcourſe hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:121348:19"/>
               <p>Theſe as exceptions premis'd,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I ſuppoſe our Author might ſafely proceed, teaching that all Verbs admit an Ablative Caſe of the Inſtrument, Cauſe, or manaer of an action. As
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>1</hi> Naturam expellas furcá licet uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> recurret.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>2</hi> Invidus alterius rebns macreſcit opimis.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>3</hi> Jam veniet tacito curva ſenecta pede.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>As if he had ſaid; The condition of thoſe and the like Ablatives are rationally obvious without a prepoſited ſign; although the firſt doth ſound alike with the Nominative, as do the other two like the Dative.</p>
               <p>For whatever moveth from its material cauſe not attracted by the formal, doth it weakly; and conſequently, in order to aſſiſtance, laterally. As is demonſtrable either by a Spider or Cyphon.<note place="margin">See the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme.</note> Elſe why cannot the Spider mount directly upwards more than the wine can continue its aſcending motion through a plain inſtrument aſwell as a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral we ſuch as the Embleme notifies?</p>
               <p>Sembl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bly in thoſe examples, the motion having no attraction from the word of Senſe [nature at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting its expulſion no more than another mans proſperity can naturally my leanneſs] muſt make uſe of a lateral help to reach it.</p>
               <p>Aud this the firſt of the ſaid examples doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>in lenminis:</hi> the Categorical word of ſenſe in the two laſt <hi>Being</hi> umbrated by the Verb: <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cit quaſi macrum ſe r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ddit.</hi> So <hi>Senecta ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ict,</hi> as if he had ſaid <hi>Nos aſſequetur ſeu depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>det.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in like manner do I apprehend the word of Price: <hi>Teruncio non emeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Something being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily underſtood that is ſo bought.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121348:20"/>
               <p>Laſtly, Whereas our Author noteth certain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>transformed paſſives, by him called Verbs depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, that govern and Ablative barely without Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or Categorical word either expreſs or underſtood: as <hi>Fungor, Fruor, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I can no way underſtand this governance as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to their ſaid voyces; while they are alſo read both with prepoſited Ablative notes and line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally caſual Accuſatives; as of <hi>utor</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollyoake</hi> obſerveth out of <hi>Gel. l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 13. And therefore do I conceive it proper for theſe and the like Verbs only when their final cauſe is incomprehenſible by the formal; the caſual word ſo ſerving as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, Cauſe, or Mode; though commonly of a motion other than that it immediately depends on, as in the <hi>Ciceronian</hi> example there produc'd <hi>Qui adipiſci veram gloriam volunt, Juſtitiae fungantur of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiis:</hi> where the motion tendeth finally towards glory; the office being us'd but as a lateral help to reach it.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe genitives he noteth as led away from this rule; the offence cannot be impardonable while their Verbs move in order to poſſeſſion; as, <hi>Hujus indigeo patris,</hi> &amp;c,</p>
               <p>Saving of his excepted <hi>Tanti, quanti, &amp;c.</hi> which I ſubmit if I may not aſwell underſtand adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bially. Sithence I can finde no reaſon why <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> may not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo taken aſwell as <hi>Quantum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enn<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>;</hi> both, and the reſt there cited, being equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly circumſtantial; and circumſtances often duly prefer'd to demonſtrations, as is Reaſon to Senſe. Whence (although the Commentator ſcruples it) I conceive the expreſſion was no way below <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronius;</hi> while on the fall<note n="*" place="margin">Whence probably our Gallants took up their toſs glaſs faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> of <hi>TRIMALIO'S</hi> Cup he thus ſung:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121348:20"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Heu heu nos miſeros quam totus homuncio nil eſt!</l>
                     <l>Sic erimus cuncti poſtquam nos auferet Orcus.</l>
                     <l>Ergo Vivamus dum licet eſſe bene.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Neither do I find the like liberty leſs Emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally taken by the Engliſh: Witneſs that of Dr. <hi>Dunne's.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Both good and well ſhould in our actions meet;</l>
                     <l>The wicked is not worſe than th' indiſcreet.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Concluſively,<note place="margin">4. Whether the Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction be our Authors I queſtion not, ſince I finde the whole en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled by his name.</note> our Author in his Introduction tels us, <q>That Verbs tranſitives are all ſuch as have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them an Accuſative caſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He might have added <hi>only</hi>] ſithence its that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance that makes a verb tranſitive.</p>
               <p>Other Verbs as well governing it accompany'd, as,
<q>
                     <l>Aeſt mo te bujus.</l>
                     <l>Do litcras tibi.</l>
                     <l>Imperti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Parmenonem ſalute.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas the tranſitive motion both directly tendeth towards, and centereth in its formal cauſe; except when it runs as it were through it by govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two accuſatives: <hi>Poſce deum veniam</hi> ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting a confidence of obtaining. Whereas we ſay <hi>Veniam Petimus ab ipſo. Quia poſcimus imperioſe; at Petimus ſubmiſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the word tranſitive, I do not remember to have read it elſewhere, ſave only in <hi>Scapula</hi> as La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenizing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The large ſignification of whoſe praepoſited part affordeth much of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the reception of this rule as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
               <p>Or if I derive it from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and then (either in imitation of the Peripatetick Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121348:21"/>or the hiſtorical conſideration of the great City in its various reſpective conditions between the ſheep-hook and the Crozier) but form a circle of Caſes: I ſhall find the Accuſative, according to its name, juſt oppoſite categorical or adverſe to the Nominative.</p>
               <p>As when I ſay <hi>John</hi> loveth <hi>Joan;</hi> there under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the action of love directly transfer'd from <hi>John</hi> to <hi>Joan;</hi> and conſequently teaching to place <hi>Joan</hi> accuſatively.</p>
               <p>Or, thirdly, if I look upon this caſe as it is the center of the variations of the Noune, becauſe placed in the midſt of five; [our Authors ſix caſes making but five variations] and then obſerve the natural intendment of all motion towards the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as its final cauſe or perfection, I muſt thence conclude this governance as natural as that <hi>John</hi> ſhould love <hi>Joan,</hi> and conſequently underſtand our Author, as telling me, That, naturally, all Verbs do expect the word of ſence ſhould ſerve Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
               <p>But ſithence that there be alſo motions of deſign; ſuch as the circular,<note place="margin">See the Emblem.</note> oblique and lateral: and that accordingly ſome Verbs move in order to poſſeſſion: others to acquiſition: and others to occaſional action. Therefore this rule is to be ſo underſtood, as that the three other forecited may be received by way of Exception.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:121348:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the Declanſions of the Word of Being, or Noune Subſtantive.</head>
               <p>THe third variation of this word of Being is according to its reſpective Declenſions. An accident by which the Latines mainly excell in their fore-noted<note n="*" place="margin">See the preface fol. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>magnum in parvo</hi> of ſpeech. So intelligibly couching the Article under the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Noune, as they do the perſon or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune under the termination of the Verb: which compells them ſo to vary the terminations of both, declining the firſt reſpectively after the five rules mentioned by our Author as followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Words Maſculine and Feminine terminating in <hi>[a]</hi> they decline after the firſt rule, as <hi>Poeta, Muſa,</hi> &amp;c. But the neutrals in <hi>[a]</hi> they decline after the third, as <hi>Dogma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the obſervance hereof is of uſe to the more ready manifeſtation of the gender: the Neuter otherwiſe not ſo ſoon occurring, in regard of their admittance of ſuch dead Beings as contain the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, among the Feminines, as in the firſt Chapter of the ſecond part hath been foreſhewed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Words Identically Maſculine and Feminine ending in <hi>[us]</hi> or <hi>[ius]</hi> they decline after the ſecond rule, as, <hi>Cibus, Fluvius, Humus:</hi> but words Feminine of quality they decline after the third, as, <hi>Salus.</hi> And ſo do they their identical Neuters, as, <hi>Foedus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But tropical neuters ſo terminatin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline after the ſecond rule. Whence ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Author
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121348:22"/>notes them among the non-creſcents, as <hi>Virus, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagus — &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereof the firſt is neutrally decline only in regard its operation ſo taken tendeth towards death;<note place="margin">Virus.</note> yet after this rule; To manifeſt that its killing energie is identical to the nature of the thing no otherwiſe than in reſpect of the <hi>Dos,</hi> and manner of its uſe: there being otherwiſe among the three natural bodies no greater Cordials than ſuch as are prepar'd of <hi>Opium, Viper,</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Naturality of the ſecond's declenſion I can not well unrevel without ſome elongation of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.<note place="margin">Pelagus.</note> It being a word beſides which the Latine hath more appellations for the Sea then any other language I know. Whereof four be moſt ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant names; viz. <hi>Fretum, Mare, Pontus</hi> and <hi>Aequor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt properly ſignifying Creeks or Ferries, which at ebbing water be rough, current, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous. Whence <hi>Fretum quaſi fervidum,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Hollyoake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond ſignifying all Seas in general;
<q>
                     <l>— Maria ac terras, caelum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Profundum</l>
                     <l>Quippe ferant rapidi—<note place="margin">Aen. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                  </q> Saith <hi>Virgil</hi> of the winds.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hollyoake</hi> derives the word from <hi>Marath</hi> of the Hebrews; which I underſtand not <hi>quoad guſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> as he there inſinuates, but <hi>quoad tranſitum.—</hi>
                  <q>Placata<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> venti dant Maria—<note place="margin">Aen. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </q> Saith the ſame Author.</p>
               <p>The third denominating vaſt Seas; and ſo ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121348:22"/>formed <hi>ab abſentiâ P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntis.</hi>
                  <q>— Coelum undi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; undi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Pontus.</q> Saith the Maronian in his fore quoted book.</p>
               <p>And the fourth even or calm Seas; <hi>ab aequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> As he elſewhere notes by <hi>Aequora tuta ſilent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reſt being rather Epithites than names, as <hi>Salum,</hi> i. e. <hi>Salſum. Caerulum,</hi> i. e. <hi>Caeruleum. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria.</hi> i. e. <hi>Hadriaticum.</hi> So <hi>Oceanus,</hi> i. e. <hi>Oceanum mare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Epithites and names ſo amply denoting the Sea in all reſpects; I know not what ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to borrow the only name that the Greek had for it<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pelagus.</note>, ſave for a more ſtrict note of that Greek ſide or arm of the Mediterranean, which over againſt <hi>Galatia</hi> and upwards, themſelves alſo called <hi>Mare mortuum:</hi> whether for its mourning colour, or the deadly fewd betwixt them and the bordering Greeks: Or elſe from <hi>môr marỽ</hi> of the Brittains (ſaid to have ſince planted with <hi>Brennius</hi> their Captain on that Greek ſide) <hi>môr</hi> in that language ſignifying a Sea, and <hi>marỽ</hi> ſtill or dead: that being the ſtilleſt (or according to the Brittiſh idiome, deadlyeſt) Sea my Countrey-men had e're before croſſed: It was rational this new word of their ſhould be declined neutrally. Yet with like caution as hath been fore-noted of <hi>Virus:</hi> the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof ſpeaking it no more neuter than <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Vulgus,</hi> as it repreſents a number of living men, muſt be Maſculine: ſaving when their joynt ſtupidity is mentioned with ſcorn by the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous. And that <hi>Catachreſtically</hi> beyond the bounds-foot of Dutch Boore, by ſo much as a living dog can be ſuppoſed better than a dead Lion.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121348:23"/>
               <p>I have dwel't longer on this particular in regard I know not but there may be more words thus va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed or at leaſtwiſe variable according to the Poet or Orator's occaſion. For, The Gender being but an affection of the Noune, becomes alterable not only according to the uſe of the thing ſpecified: but alſo to the preſent paſſion or paſſionate recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame.
<q>Accede ad ignem hanc —</q> ſaith <hi>Terence</hi> in <hi>Eunuchus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I return to our declenſions: where the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Maſculines and tropical Feminines in <hi>[us]</hi> I obſerve declinable after the fourth rule, as <hi>Potus, Domus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ignorami ſocius.</note> &amp;c. Whereupon if the Queſtion of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantius</hi> in the Play ſhould be renewed, viz. <hi>Cur non Potus facit Poti ſicut cibus cibi in genitivo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The anſwer would be, That the firſt is ſuppoſed to be either water or the juice of vegetives: but the other properly living creatures: as is obſerved by the Engliſh, while they call nothing <hi>meat</hi> but fleſh.</p>
               <p>Or if it ſhould he ask'd, Why <hi>morbus</hi> is declin'd after the ſecond rule, and <hi>ſalus</hi> after the third?</p>
               <p>The anſwer were, That the ſecond is but a meer qualitative Being, but the firſt a ſubſtantial one. For, (as the learned <hi>Capivaccius</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In cap. de P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiſi.</note> hath it) <hi>Omnis morbus eſt vel vapor vel minera.</hi> Thereby excluding all the pretended diſeaſes <hi>ab inanitione:</hi> becauſe until there be a peccant matter, as there can be no inequality, ſo no pain. It being a maxime in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine that <hi>Doloriſica actio fit à proportione majoris in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequalitatis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(a)</note>
               </p>
               <p>There do alſo belong to this declenſion all words ending in <hi>[um]</hi> and <hi>[ir]</hi> and likewiſe ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121348:23"/>flouriſhing Maſculine in <hi>[er].</hi> Others ſo termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating being rationally transfer'd to the third rule: as in the next Chapter ſhall be ſhewed.</p>
               <p>But as for our Author's <hi>Satur,</hi> I cannot finde it ſubſtantially poſited by any Latine writer: neither any word ſo terminating declinable after this rule.</p>
               <p>The third claiming both that and all other not forementioned terminations whatſoever: having of late left none declinable after the fifth. Save only the monoſyllable <hi>Res,</hi> and ſuch as terminate in <hi>[ies].</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>fraus boneſta,</hi> which I ſuppoſe committed in meer order to the quadrupedation of Heroick verſe. <hi>Plebs</hi> after the old way of declining Being, when obliquely caſual, thereby comprehenſible no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as the myrabolan nut of the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie's.
<q>
                     <l>Quod nec <hi>Virgilius,</hi> nec carmine dixit <hi>Homerus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hoc ex unguento conſtat &amp; ex balano.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121348:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of the ſenſuality of the caſual word: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this Tract called a word of ſence. Alſo of the declenſion of the word of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</head>
               <p>HAving in the firſt Chapter of the firſt part of this Tract ſhewed that the word of Being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſenſual by mediation of Quality.</p>
               <p>And, in the third, that the ſignification of this Quality can be ſenſually faſhion'd no otherwiſe than as either joyned or inſerted to a Being: It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains that the manner of this union be yet further examined.</p>
               <p>The Angel in the Text (as checking the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious enquiry of <hi>Eſdras</hi>) is ſaid to have bid <q>him meaſure an handful of wind,<note place="margin">Eſdr. <hi>2, 4.</hi>
                     </note> and weigh an ounce of fire.</q>
               </p>
               <p>A curioſity which the ſons of <hi>Hermes</hi> yet ceaſe not to purſue; By an unwearied attempt to loſen the fire from its entitative fixation: that ſo incorporat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf with the volateeles, it may, by their rule of rotation, ſo defaecated, entice thoſe ſpirits with it inſeparably to cohabit <hi>Ad perpetrandum miracula unius rei.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Tab.</note> Saith that Father.</p>
               <p>However this be not commonly known to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the practice: The poſſibility of the work may, happily, appear leſs worthily ridiculous: If the forecited proceſs be but compar'd with what we may hourly obſerve in common converſe: <hi>viz.</hi> How that by declining a word of Being from its denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121348:24"/>ſtate or condition, the hinges of its other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe immoveable eſſence are ſo ſhaken, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thereby fitted for ſuch a coition with incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal quality, as doth rationally advance it to an excellency enabling its reception or all the ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Beings whatſoever. Inſomuch that the numberleſs notions of man are thereby made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative; although the quality of the word have no outward appearance therein at all.</p>
               <p>As to reinſtance: when I ſay <hi>JOHN LO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VETH JOAN;</hi> the very Grammatically caſual poſition of <hi>Joan,</hi> as the formal cauſe of <hi>Johns</hi> love, ſheweth in her ſome perfection wanted by <hi>John.</hi> Whether <hi>qua animal</hi> for the perpetuation of his entity; or alſo <hi>qua rationale,</hi> in order to future conveniency of living. And ſo <hi>John</hi> loveth <hi>Joan</hi> either ſo fair, young, rich, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhall adjudge moſt for his own felicity. Which to underſtand is the ſumme of all Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Syntax. The queſtion and its anſwer being alike modable: and all definitive, ſentences either reſolving a queſtion already propounded; or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting their anſwer, by confirmation, contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or deſired illuſtration from the confabulant. So that whatever elſe can be expreſſed is but <hi>ad voluptatem linguae,</hi> and on this depending. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall endeavour to render it yet more plain and perſpicuous: Even by a Fable read of old by <hi>Diotima</hi> to <hi>Socrates</hi> Where ſhe feigneth how that as the Gods were celebrating the birth-day of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Porus</hi> the ſon of Providence and God of Wealth ſhould be there amongſt them: and, got drunk, ſhould, as he went forth to caſe him, fall aſleep at the Gate where <hi>Poenia</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>overty waited for an Alms: Which ſhe obſerving; That the indigency of her condition overcoming the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121348:25"/>of her ſex, ſhould prompt her to allure <hi>Porus</hi> to a congreſs, whereby ſhe conceived and brought forth <hi>Love;</hi> who ever ſince hath been a cloſe companion of <hi>Venus;</hi> becauſe begotten on her birth-feaſt, as aforeſaid,</p>
               <p>By the ſame reaſon is the word of Senſe as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable from its inviſible quality. And is the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, I mean worded Quality or Adjective ever declined according to the ſubſtantial naturality of that word: as by our Authors three firſt rules for declenſion of nou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es appeareth: <hi>Bonus domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Bona muſa, Bonum regnum: Triſtis Pareus, Triſte Cadaver, Faelix natalis; liber Magiſter, libera Magiſtra, liberum Magiſterium;</hi> few or no Adjectives terminating in <hi>[er]</hi> being otherwiſe declinable. <hi>Acer, Pauper, Degener</hi> and <hi>Uber</hi> ſo mentioned by our Author, being as often read The firſt <hi>Acris;</hi> and the ſecond, in no meaner Author than <hi>Plautus, Paupera.</hi> So that theſe are little better than He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troclites; as the third is than a degenerate ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive, <hi>viz.</hi> a Subſtantive foyld with a prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo turn'd Adjective <hi>de genere;</hi> and the fourth being a meer derivative <hi>Ube ab Ubere.</hi> So alſo proving firſt that thoſe Subſtantives in <hi>[er]</hi> which be declined after our Author's ſecond rule are naturally excelling thoſe that be transfer'd to the third:<note place="margin">(a)</note> which are either Feminine as <hi>Mater;</hi> or dividing from their unity as <hi>frater;</hi> or elſe in the declination of the vigour of their Maſculine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as <hi>Pater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, it proveth that our Author's two laſt rules for declenſion of Subſtantives were by the refiners of the Latine added.<note place="margin">(B)</note> The one to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh ſuch words terminating in <hi>[us]</hi> as they were pleaſed by the aſſiſtance of their Tropes to advance either from their naturali neutrality to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121348:25"/>the Feminine gender, as <hi>Domus:</hi> or from their muliebrity to the Maſculine as <hi>Potus:</hi> which as it is water ſhould be declin'd Femininely: but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of its nouriſhing uſe ſhall be declin'd Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culinely; yet after the fourth rule: In order firſt to a diſtinction between it and an Identical Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line: and ſecondly for manifeſtation of its advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing trope.</p>
               <p>As for words ending in <hi>[U]</hi> their Heteroclity pronounceth them but vulgarly regular; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of a leſs eſteem than the former, in regard they are all Neuters.</p>
               <p>The fiſt of our Authors rules as it was added ſo was it repeal'd. The celebration of Heroick verſe having for the moſt part rendred it imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent if not offenſive, as in the foregoing Chapter hath been foreſhewed.</p>
               <p>Therefore have theſe rules no Adjective de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable after their terminations. The Latine Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as well in its declenſions as gradual aſcentions being ſtrictly worded after the forecited Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie of<note n="*" place="margin">Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Ternarii largè vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri eſt apud <hi>Gerard.</hi> Dorn. in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiâ Chem. Trithem. in Ep. ad Gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. alioſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorum paſſim. Viz. <hi>in the uſes.</hi>
                  </note> Vertue; though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll three ſound alike from vulgar tongues.</p>
               <p>Which worthily magnifies the Roman Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in framing their rules ſo that thereby words as well as things ſhould bear their witneſs.</p>
               <p>Of which hereafter —</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:121348:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of number, with the Arts thereout eman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</head>
               <p>THis accident might deſervedly have challenged the firſt place in reſpect the others could not be diſcuſſed without it: the Genders, Caſes, and Declenſions of the Noune being all diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by vertue of number. Yet becauſe of its ſmall uſe in Grammer Syntax, I thought fit to marſhal it here in the arrear of the declenſion of the Adjective: its multiplication ſo taken amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to little more than the Adjective's Even and Odd. For as even and odd cannot ſtand together in one number; ſo may not the ſame number be both ſingular and plurally accounted; the leaſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the ſingular rendring it plural; and the moſt doing no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Therefore are we glad to aſcertain the unities by the addition of a quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative quality, As to ſay, two, three, four, five, and ſo to the end of Arithmetick. By the Antients compil'd to an Art according to their four rules of <hi>ADDITION, SUBSTRACTION, MULTIPLICATION,</hi> and <hi>DIVISI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which laſt they extended even to the diviſion of an unity; and ſo produced two arts more: whereof the one they called Geometrie, and the other Aſtronomie; the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifying both number, order, and harmonie: The laſt whereof originally to proceed from the motion of the ſpheres; and conſequently its knowledge as an
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121348:26"/>Art from the ſpherical part of Aſtronomie, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to need no better proof than what <hi>Cicero</hi> hath left us in his tranſcendent tract <hi>de</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Legitur inter frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceronis.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Somnio Scipionis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other notes on this accident obſerveable find I none. Save that cuſtom doth herein overſway both order, nature and reaſon. As (to ſay nothing of the<note n="*" place="margin">It is known to every one to what caſe the royal bloods of <hi>Portugal</hi> is driven. <hi>Los San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues</hi> — So <hi>Don E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel</hi> in Reaſons for his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, p. 8.</note> received civil difference between per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages in point of extraction) when mentioning the ſmoak of an hundred Chimneys exhaling, perhaps, from as many reſpective combuſtible ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials: Or Latinizing all the ſands between <hi>Callis</hi> and <hi>Gravellin,</hi> I muſt expreſs my ſelf ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly. Whereas traveling but a little further Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I ſhall finde the damp'd mudd whereon thoſe Towns ſtand call'd by name of <hi>THE UNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED PROVINCES OF THE NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERLANDS.</hi> An <hi>Alleotheta</hi> of ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ornament as I have but ſmall encouragement to endeavour the diſſwaſion of the Engliſh Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees from owning for good genuine ſenſe, by any addition of ſucceſs my experience found the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary reaſoning of their <hi>Scaliger</hi> to have gained on his <hi>Houghen Moughens</hi> there; his words on the place being theſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Terrae diviſionem auſpicati ſunt à familiaribus occupationibus; Et jus ipſam injuriam apellarunt; Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> enim m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lius terra d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>buit alii atque alii tribui quam aer.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 176.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I aque natura vindicat ſeſe; &amp; mortuos Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos non majore tegit tumulo, quam unum ex opreſsis: ſeſe omnibus aequalem oſtendens matrem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Yet for certain plurally recorded feſtivals; ſince on their daies there were alſo kept Fairs, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to mention them accordingly, was but rational. As the old Romans did their <hi>Floralia,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121348:27"/>Bacchanalia,</hi> &amp;c. No more is it to name the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acervation of many into one ſingularly, as <hi>populus, pars,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Species</hi> or Shapes,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Specus, uns de ſpecies.</note> and Figures; which are our Author's other accidents of a Noune: finding them of a meer external conſideration, I paſs; as not competent to the intrinſecal deſign of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:121348:27"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Herm'aelogium;</hi> The third PART.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Shewing the variations and affections of the word of Motion. And firſt of its diſtinguiſhment by number and perſon: Alſo of the Verb imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T deſcends firſt from its<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Anher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bhynedig bhôd.</hi> Themate primario. So Dr. <hi>Das vis,</hi> p. 83.</note> 
                  <hi>Infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Eſſence</hi> in order to an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate concordancie with the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whence it proceeds, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and perſon: <hi>I, THOU</hi> or <hi>HE; WE, YE</hi> or <hi>THEY;</hi> under whom be comprehended, and by which are perſonated the Baſis of all motion whatſoever. All Verbs whereby on ſpeaks to a Being, of whatever
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121348:28"/>Gender, being naturally perſonable after the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. And all by which mention is made of a thing or things (except of ones ſelf or of things joyned to himſelf) being after the third. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Latines not only decline the note of the third perſon as a Pronoune Adjective; but alſo manifeſt the eſteem and ſingularity of the Being it under that<note n="*" place="margin">And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo the others, as, <hi>Ego <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u ipſe,</hi> &amp;c.</note> perſon repreſents, by their triplicit diſtinction of <hi>Ille, Ipſe,</hi> and <hi>Iſte:</hi> much as the Engliſh <hi>Thon</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> ſo much cavil'd at by our zealous Tremblers.</p>
               <p>Since then every motion neceſſarily proceedeth from a Being as comprehenſible by theſe pronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal perſons, ſome or one of them. It follows that there can be no ſuch thing as a Verb imperſonal ſtrictly taken; more then that there may be Gold without weight and fixation. Wherefore our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in his Inſtitutions declareth his acceptation of that name in a larger ſenſe: by telling us not of a Verb that diſtinguiſheth none; but that doth not vary in point of perſonality. <q>Being declined throughout all Moods and Tences in the voice of the third perſon ſingular only.</q>
               </p>
               <p>What might induce the Ancients to the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a Verb, I only gueſs as by comparing exterior organick motions with the mental. The perfection of the firſt being in its end; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thitherward followed by the eye of the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator, with avidity more or leſs, as the motion tendeth towards acquiſition: that, in reſpect of its grandizing faculty, being appetible equally with Good: as the contrary is avoydable like hurt or Evill.</p>
               <p>Hence comes it not only that young fencers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſhut their eyes at the ſtrokes of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and that we enjoy thoſe pleaſures which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121348:28"/>end in loſs with more freedom of delight in the dark; but alſo do account it a fortitude not to contract and guard our eyes if a Hawk ſhould but offer to ſowce at our face; although we behold her flight at a fowl with comparative delight. The like might be inſtanced by a Shaft or Bowl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame 'tis with the Eye of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And therefore when the material cauſe of the motion is moſt worthy our obſervation, the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents might rationally marſhal it in the arrear of the formal; as ſaying, <hi>Oportet mendacem eſſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem:</hi> where the two laſt words are the Baſis or material cauſe of <hi>oportet;</hi> which, were they plac'd in the from of the ſentence, would render the Verb Perſonal, [for we alſo read <hi>oporteo</hi>] and ſo the attention would be attracted towards <hi>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem</hi> as the formal cauſe of a tranſitive motion: which were divers from the intent of the ſentence; The memnonic Art being of ſuch neceſſary uſe to a Lyar, that without it he could never hope to thrive by his faculty.</p>
               <p>Thus as the Paſſive voyce rendreth the proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of its motion comparatively excelling the Active by meer addition of the letter <hi>[R]</hi> and tranſpoſition of its extreams, as hath been<note n="*" place="margin">Part. 1. c. 2.</note> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed, doth the fixation of a Verb in this third perſon with a retirement of its material cauſe to the arrear of the formal, declare a vehemency no leſs then ſuperlatively notable.</p>
               <p>Which leadeth me to the obſervation of two like Ceremonies uſual in humanity; whereof the one is our incitation of importunity, or more earneſt ſolicitation, by a Maiden refuſal of what in covert we ambiently affect; like the Biſhops<note n="*" place="margin">Mes erat apud An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glos ut Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopo promoventi, Epiſcopa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ter (vel ob modeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am) reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret Nolo.</note> 
                  <hi>Nolo;</hi> or that coy dame of whom <hi>Virgil</hi> ſings:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121348:29"/>
                  <q>Et fugit ad ſalices, &amp; ſe cupit ante videri.<note place="margin">Ecl. 3.</note>
                  </q> The other is, our manifeſtation of reſpect towards our Confabulant by ſo perſonating him according to his attributes. <hi>Dominatio veſtra</hi> being the article of ſalute beyond the Seas even between ſingle Gentlemen; which in <hi>England</hi> is in faſhion only among the greater Nobility. Except while a Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, to ſhew his reſpective diſtance, affordeth the attribute of <hi>WORSHIP</hi> to the leſſer. And to the ſame end alſo is the firſt Perſon ſo convertible; as when for [I am] we ſay [Your Servant is]. The dignity of this number being celebrated even by our natural unpoliſhed geſtures. In that the firſt and ſecond perſons of the Verb be aſwell digitally as vocally notified; but this third perſon never digitally, ſaving in order to contempt. so that it was not without reaſon that the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it for the heightning of perſwaſion. As Sir <hi>Geoffery Chaucer</hi> when repreſenting the Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Alchymiſt
<q>
                     <l>— Thus ſaid he in his game,<note place="margin">The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans tale.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Stoopeth a down in faith you be to blame.</l>
                     <l>Delpeth me now, as I did you wylere,</l>
                     <l>Put in your hond looketh what is there.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>There is another ſort of Verb which Mr. <hi>Hoole</hi> in his<note n="*" place="margin">Page 147.</note> Grammar calleth Verbs of an exempt power, as <hi>Fulgurat, Tonitruit,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe (ſaith he) (though he is pleas'd to declare the nature of neither) come near the nature of imperſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</p>
               <p>The neerneſs I find to conſiſt meerly in their fixation in this Superlative ſingularity of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121348:29"/>and that only by vertue of a reciprocality <hi>è contrario.</hi> Theſe laſt, until their cauſes were known, being apprehended with a kind of timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous admiration; and therefore imitating the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhutting of the eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I heard thy voice in the Garden</hi> (ſaid <hi>Adam</hi> in the Text) <hi>and I was afraid and did my ſelf.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>From all which I conclude that however I read the third perſon ſingular of a Verb Active uſurp'd; I am thereby to underſtand a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency; yet not equal with our Authors imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonals, unleſs alſo the Baſis be poſt-poſited as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The Verb Imperſonal of the Paſſive Voice I obſerve to vary from the ſenſe of its perſonality only while it fixeth our obſervance to it ſelf; juſt as the fore-quoted noble <hi>Chaucer</hi> doth by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Active, where<note n="*" place="margin">In Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of fowls.</note> he thus ſingeth:
<q>
                     <l>As from awd ground MENSAITH com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Corn fro yeer to year.</l>
                     <l>So from a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d Books, by my faith, commen all new Science that men lere.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Spoke though ſingular being ſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd more conſiderable than the plurality of the ſpeakers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:121348:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Conjugations of the Latine Verb.</head>
               <p>THe main end of this and the following varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as Roman, being<note n="*" place="margin">In Preface fol. 2.</note> already manifeſted. It remains that their reſpective both natural and vocal inclinations be now examined.</p>
               <p>The firſt whereof uſeleſs in vulgar tongues, which for the moſt part expreſs the Mood and Tenſe by prepoſited notes, The <hi>Latines,</hi> doing it by their various ſhaping of the Terminations, were therefore forc'd, as for the declining of their Noun, ſo of their Verb, to invent Rules varying by alike reaſon, according to the ſound and nature of the word; which rules they were pleasd to make known by name of <hi>CONJUGATIONS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether by a Metaphor <hi>à Con ugio</hi> in regard that without theſe the conjugated Pronoun cannot be made a <hi>femme covert</hi> (as our law renders it) Iſcruple not.</p>
               <p>Only obſerve that as all Active <hi>Latine</hi> Verbs do terminate either in <hi>[o] [co]</hi> or <hi>[io]</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the language noteth no more Conjuga ions <hi>i</hi> &amp; thence conclude our Authors third Conjugation to be [even as the<note n="*" place="margin">Part. 2. c. 4. (B).</note> forementioned two laſt Declenſions of the Noun] added, meerly for a diſtinguiſher of ſuch Verbs as, by the ſame or like ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, convey a different ſignification; whereof the ſignificator of the moſt worthy action terminating in <hi>[o]</hi> ſhall be of the firſt, and the leſs worthy ſhall be of the third Conjugation. As for inſtance, That word<note n="*" place="margin">Lego.</note> by which our Author exemplifieth this Conjugation we alſo read declinable after the firſt. But ſithence
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121348:30"/>To ſet a houſe in order, or to perform an Embaſſie be actions ſo far tranſcending Reading, Stealing or gathering of hearbs; although the language preſents all alike; yet its no ſmall demonſtration of its curioſity that the word is diverſly conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated.</p>
               <p>And as Verbs declinable after this Conjugation do, on this and ſuch like an account, deſcend to the third; ſo do others of the fourth aſcend to it.<note place="margin">How genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inely then ſome Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors do confound the Infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of both I ſubmit.</note> As for example: They properly decline <hi>Cupio</hi> after the fourth; in regard it denotes want: but <hi>Capio</hi> becauſe it expreſſeth the recovery or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of a thing fore-wanted [although it alſo ends in <hi>[io]</hi> they ſtrictly decline after the third; which moreover I obſerve ſo placed, becauſe
<q>
                     <l>— Facile eſt deſcenſus Averni;</l>
                     <l>Sed revocare gradum; bic labor —</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding I find that ſome Verbs deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative from Nounes tetminating in <hi>[io]</hi> ſtick not in their aſcent even to the firſt Conjugation: as, <hi>Somnio</hi> from <hi>Somnium,</hi> &amp;c. And on that ſcore have we alſo ſome Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s terminating in <hi>[eo]</hi> ſo conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, as <hi>Calceo</hi> from <hi>Calceus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Contrarily <hi>Eo, queo, veneo</hi> do deſcend to the fourth. So by their Conjugation as well as Form proclaiming their Heteroclity: though not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: as <hi>aio, Cedo, Salve,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:121348:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Moods and Tenſes.</head>
               <p>THe Conjugations lead me thirdly to the Moods; which are modes, ſhapes or faces of the Verb carved according to the inclination of the minde for the ſtating of a motion under a certain time.</p>
               <p>Of whoſe nature or product finding ſo full an account rendred by the learned<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid c. 114</note> 
                  <hi>Scaliger,</hi> I ſhall not ſhew my ſelf ſo much a Plagiary as to inſert it otherwiſe than as the ſenſe of his more able pen, which ſummarily is:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That all things which act muſt needs be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with an appetible energie or power to deſire: that being the cauſe of motion as <hi>PRIVATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON</hi> is of It; and whatever it be that deſireth, doth it either inconſiderately by a certain natural propenſion, ſuch as is the fires to burn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elſe adviſedly.</p>
                  <p>Which laſt ſort o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſire ſtandeth equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to two contraries; as a man's either to walk or not. In which alſo there muſt be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain deliberation; that is, an affection of the mind freely reaſoning this election; whether <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con</hi> makes no difference. Sithence he that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth doth perſwade not to do.</p>
                  <p>Whence it was neceſſary that things thus done ſhould be declared by a particular ſhape, face, or figure of words. Therefore things juſt now done they called Indicative or Definitive. Things to be done before this election, or on it depending they called <hi>con</hi> or Subjunctive. Things abſolute
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121348:31"/>or no way depending and yet in the power of another they diſtinguiſhed; calling a vote to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a greater Optative; and towards a leſſer Imperative.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, whereas certain Verbs do barely expreſs the will, power or Inclination of the agent: as, <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, cup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o, vadeo, &amp;c.</hi> The object of thoſe are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible either ſimply, or elſe under time: thus, <hi>Volo cibum, cupio imperium, video curſum.</hi> Meat being ſimply objected to the will; Rule to the deſire; and the courſe or race to the ſight.</p>
                  <p>But if I were to manifeſt theſe objects under time and action joyntly: then were I forc'd to find out ſome word that might expreſs the action Infinitively: that is, without Poſitively defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning either; as to ſay: <hi>Volo comedere, cupio im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare, video te currere.</hi> Which infinitive way of expreſſion cannot yet properly be called a Mood; ſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence no inclination of the mind is by it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Thus far <hi>Scaliger.</hi> So comprehending firſt the queſtioning Mood of the Ancients under the Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, Definitive or Indicative. Secondly, the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative under the Imperative; and thirdly, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Infit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tive as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hoole</hi> (whoſe pardon I ſhall not deſpair of, if I tranſgreſs the mode by quoting them in their dayes, when they know that ſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling this at my paternal hermitage in <hi>Glamorgan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> beſides their and the fore-cited, I had the ſight of no track on this Subject) Although out of compliance with our Author they retain the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitive, yet make but one Mood of the Optative, Potential and Subjunctive. And in my opinion as tolerably. For if <hi>Scaliger</hi> couldmaintain his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion for want of a power to particularize a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121348:32"/>inclination of the minde: why might not they their reduction,<note place="margin">See the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition.</note> all three being expreſſible under one figure or face?</p>
               <p>Beſides that the two laſt are not eſſential to the Philoſophy, but multilocution of a ſentence, <hi>viz</hi> that thereby two ſentences might be expreſſible at once. The ſound of the Potential <hi>Latine</hi> Mood, when ſingle, being alwayes expreſſed by the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Poſſum, Volo</hi> or <hi>Debeo.</hi> And the Subjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive elſewhere quot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by <hi>Scaliger,</hi> (and that as the ſenſe of an Ancient) to be <hi>Nonita dictus quia ſubjungeretur, ſed quia ſubjungeret.</hi> So implicit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſing its defect, until another be joyned to it.</p>
               <p>The ſame might be ſaid of the Potential; which, ſo placed, as it intelligibly comprehends <hi>Poſſum, &amp;c</hi> is thereby made capable of the name. So that as the Optative Mood is known by its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb; and the Subjunctive by its conjunction; the Potential is manifeſted by its Subjunctive of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, without either Adverb or Conjunction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to joyned, under the face of an Optative.</p>
               <p>But whether the Subjunctive deſerves the honor of the name, as Mr. <hi>Hoole.</hi> Or the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential, as Dr. <hi>Taylor;</hi> Or the Optative added to the Subjunctive, as <hi>Scaliger.</hi> Or ſince we can well explode neither with preſervation of the language from its ancient barbarity, whether it be not ſafeſt to retain them all as we find them ranked by our Author, I ſhall not undertake to determine.</p>
               <p>Only obſerve that the firſt intention of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in and by the whole, but teacheth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably to queſtion, define, require, perſwade or wiſh according to the three formal differences of time whether preſent, paſt, or to come.</p>
               <p>The ſub-diviſion of the time paſt into <hi>[Did]
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121348:32"/>[Have]</hi> and <hi>[Had]</hi> appearing to have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented on the ſame account with the three laſt noted Moods. The <hi>Ictus</hi> or nick of time being of ſuch quickneſs as preventeth our notice. So that fitſt; To ſay an action is imperfectly paſſed is the ſame as to ſay It is paſſed and not paſſed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the exacteſt <hi>Latin</hi> Writers have uſed both promiſcuouſly.</p>
               <p>So that as for <hi>Virgils</hi> authority cited in mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the contrary, where he ſings
<q>
                     <l>Hìc Templum Junoni ingens Sidonia Dido</l>
                     <l>Condebat —<note place="margin">Aeneid. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                  </q> On which our Author comments <hi>Erat enim adhuc in opere.</hi> I conceive our Author is there to be underſtood <hi>Cum grano Salis,</hi> even as is the Poet. To whoſe deſign then in hand, I think I need not be thought at all to derogate from his known me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if I allude a note of <hi>Ben. Johnſons, viz.</hi> That
<q>
                     <l>—Poet never credit gain'd,</l>
                     <l>By writing truth, but things like truth well fain'd.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Chronologers agreeing that <hi>Troy</hi> was taken in the third year of <hi>HABDON,</hi> Judge of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See <hi>Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> And a Monument, yet remaining near old <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſhewing that the builders or fortifiers of the place were of the ſons of <hi>Anack,</hi> who had thither fled from the face of that great Robber: So they call'd <hi>Joſhua</hi> the ſon of <hi>Nun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet the cauſe of the firſt <hi>Punic</hi> war being by<note n="*" place="margin">See Sir <hi>Walter R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi>'s Hiſt. of the world. <hi>l. c. c.</hi> 5.</note> Hiſtoriographers rendred as ſcarſe honorable on the <hi>Roman</hi> ſide; It might be allowable in <hi>Virgil</hi> ſo to repreſent both that Queen, Place and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. To the end that, <hi>Aeneas</hi> his deſertion being once believed to have been by an eſpecial<note n="*" place="margin">Aeocid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> command from <hi>Jupiter,</hi> he might thereon ſtate a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121348:33"/>Theme for ſuch a Tract on that war as ſhould much vindicate the reputation of his Countrymen. For, As the <hi>Greeks,</hi> waging againſt them as <hi>Trojans</hi> for their uſurpation of a Lady, prevailed. The <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> grounding their quarrel againſt them as <hi>Romans</hi> on a cauſe contrary, might by the ſame Juſtice be render'd Authors of their own ruine. And thence might he conclude with very ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dehortatives from effeminacy; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements to a perſeverance in that proweſs which already had deified their <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But be it as the Poet there fanſieth. It appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it was the verſe and not the imperfection of the building that invited him to that expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The words following being
<q>—Donis opulentum &amp; numine Divae.</q> Otherwiſe I ſubmit it whether he might not have expreſſed himſelf by <hi>Condidit</hi> as properly as <hi>Cicero</hi> could write <hi>ad Atticum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. — ad Attic.</note> that <hi>Poſtridiè manè ad eum vadebat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To ſay it is more then perfectly paſſed is as to add to perfection. Beſides that <hi>HAD</hi> (except in certain <hi>Engliſh</hi> expreſſions of the having motion, as I had, would have had, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is of no uſe in a ſingle ſentence; And therefore cannot be more then as a Verbial Conjunction of paſs'd acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs in order to the foreſaid deſign in Elocution, we ſhall find both theſe Carabines of the Pretertenſe to be of excellent and preciſe uſe. As If I were to ſay, <hi>When I had ſpoken I ſate down.</hi> It were as if I had ſaid <hi>Did fit.</hi> But in caſe the expreſſion of the Action were to <hi>antecede</hi> the Subjunctive declaration, then <hi>HAVE</hi> would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121348:33"/>be as proper. As to ſay: <hi>He ſpoke as he had been an Oracle,</hi> i. e. <hi>Did ſpeak or hath ſpoken.</hi> And if I were to begin with the ſuppoſition; Then were I to expreſs the following action Perfectively; as to ſay: <hi>Had he been au Oracle he could not have more truly ſpoken.</hi> Which ſenſe in the <hi>Latine</hi> muſt ſound Preter-perfectively. As; <hi>Si adeſſet Apollo, rectius loqui non potuiſſet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where its obſervable that in that language the anteceding ſuppoſition is expreſſible by the Preterimperfect as well as the Pluperfect tenſe, but never by the Perfect: <hi>adfuerit,</hi> in that place, ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more like the Future tenſe.</p>
               <p>So that the conveniencie of theſe and ſuch like connections adviſe us here to underſtand <hi>Plus</hi> not as it comes from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Plenius;</hi> but from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>multus</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo may we admit of this Preterpluper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect tenſe; as being a Tenſe beſides, or rather by the ſide of the Perfect, expreſſing ſomething more: that is; ſomewhat elſe ſuffered or done before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121348:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Participial Variation of the Verb.</head>
               <p>THe Participle I take for a ſort of <hi>Motus per ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens</hi> or a moving Quality. The Verb ſo coming adjectible to a Being for manifeſtation of its qualities in order to Action or Paſſion, and that in point of time either preſent or to come.</p>
               <p>I ſay <hi>ADJECTIBLE:</hi> in regard it muſt then adhere to the Subſtantive in all reſpects like the Adjective after whoſe Termination it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined.</p>
               <p>I ſay <hi>IN ORDER TO ACTION OR PASSION:</hi> To diſtinguiſh it from a Noun Adjective; whoſe part is to expreſs the quality of the Being in order to perfection; under which I comprehend Good and Evil, as all other qualities under them.</p>
               <p>I ſay <hi>IN POINT OF TIME:</hi> To di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh it, not only from the Verbial Adjective, as; <hi>Tempus edax rerum;</hi> which, if I convert to a Participial expreſſion, muſt be <hi>Edens res;</hi> But alſo from Participial voyces and Nouns. That is: Not the Gerunds, ſo called by our Author. But Participles that be ſo only Vocally. As when I ſay: A Loving man: The word Loving is a plain Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal<note n="*" place="margin">The ſame is <hi>Caredig</hi> &amp; <hi>Caradỽu</hi> in the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh.</hi>
                  </note> Participle; there being no ſuch Adjective in the Language.</p>
               <p>Or when in <hi>Latine</hi> I ſay <hi>Legendis veteribus; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendis</hi> being Vocally a paſſive Participle of the Future tenſe.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:121348:34"/>
               <p>Yet in regard, thus poſited, thoſe no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifie no time, they are in ſenſe no more then Adjectives.</p>
               <p>Wherefore our Author teacheth, <q>That a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiple taketh part of a Verb, as Tenſe and Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</q> As if he had ſaid: The Vocality cannot make a compleat Participle, unleſs alſo it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to a Tenſe.</p>
               <p>Which, laſtly, I have here confin'd to either <hi>PRESENT</hi> or <hi>FUTURE;</hi> to manifeſt that all Qualities muſt be underſtood of Beings either Actual or Potential; Sithence a third diſtinction of Being is not to be found in Nature. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies, whether complex'd or incomplex'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but <hi>Vel praeſentia vel futura.</hi> So <hi>Jacob. Martin. in part. Met. Sect.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Thereby clearly excluding our Authors Praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe Paſſive. And, in my conceit, juſtly. For, in confirmation of <hi>Martins</hi> ſaid Philoſophy, I obſerve that this Preter-participle doth not anſwer our Authors definition.</p>
               <p>Firſt in reſpect that, in ſingle ſentences,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it doth not take, but is part of a Verb. Although the Verb or Verbial part of the word be not alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. As in that example by our Author produced out of <hi>Virgil.</hi>
                  <q>Nunc oblita mihi tot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>armina—</q> As if he had ſaid, <hi>Oblita ſunt, fuerunt vel fuere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly: That in multilocutorie or compound expreſſions the time is not noted by it,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but by the following Verb. As when I ſay <hi>Luſtratus urbem rus ibam;</hi> or <hi>ibo.</hi> The latter (being the ſame in ſenſe, as if I ſaid <hi>Poſtquam urbem luſtratus fuero, rus tho</hi>) doth manifeſt that the time in the former is not ſpecified by <hi>Luſtratus;</hi> but by the Verb <hi>tham.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121348:35"/>
               <p>Wherefore I ſubmit to my more judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether I may not here cloſe with the Rythme. (I think it be Sir <hi>William Davenants.</hi>)
<q>
                     <l>Think no more on what is paſt,</l>
                     <l>Since time in motion makes ſuch haſt.</l>
                     <l>It hath no leiſure to deſcry</l>
                     <l>The Errors which it paſſeth by.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus alſo becometh the Participle of ſo covert a cognizance, but moſt to the <hi>Latine</hi> liberty of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whereas the Northern languages, having the leaſt radical dependance on the <hi>Roman,</hi> do mainly ſo manifeſt it<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> By ranging their words according to their pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> yet after the reſpectively different Idioms following.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> always placeth the Adjective in the van of the Subſtantive; and the Participle in the arrear either of the Subſtantive or Verb: as when they ſay: <hi>A good man loving vertue liveth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly.</hi> The word <hi>Loving</hi> is ſufficiently known to be a Participle meerly becauſe placed after the Subſtantive <hi>man,</hi> and not before it as the Adjective <hi>Good.</hi> And rationally: A main uſe of the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being by the Omiſſion of a Conjunction to bring two motions that accidentally proceed from one Being expreſſible alſo by one ſentence.</p>
               <p>As for further inſtance: To read and to write are different actions. Yet its poſſible they may at once proceed from the ſame Agent: At which time, inſteed of I write and I read, I may, ſo, more concinly ſay that I write reading.</p>
               <p>So a good man may be a bad Citizen. But when both capacities well qualified do meet in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: whereas verbially I muſt have ſaid, That good man loveth vertue and liveth uprightly; I may participially expreſs all by one ſentence, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121348:35"/>That good man loving vertue liveth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame poſition have all the languages coming from the <hi>Schlavonic</hi> and <hi>High-dutch</hi> which I have heard ſundry Gentlemen of thoſe Countries main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to be originally but one. Thoſe that were otherwiſe minded ever diſputing the antiquity of tother language.</p>
               <p>Contrarily the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> (being a language of more reality then complement) as it alwayes placeth the Subſtantive in the front (it being non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe to them to prefer accidents to their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances) ſo, when the caſual word is regular without a prepoſited note, doth their participial ſenſe follow the Adjective like a middle gerund of the <hi>Latine: Gỽr da yn caru rhinỽedh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I. e. Vir bonus in amando virtutem. (En aimant</hi> ſaith the <hi>Frenchman.</hi>)</p>
               <p>An Idiome fully ratified in the ſenſe of the fore-quoted flower of <hi>Leyden</hi> where he ſaith;<note place="margin">Iul. Seal. ib. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>143.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Medium gerundiorum ſervat vires participii: Sed tanto apti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore modo quanto ſuperabantur à participiis verba.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we muſt, with<note n="*" place="margin">In prafat. ad Ethic.</note> Dr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> confeſs that <hi>Ruina Bangorienſi gloria Walliae nebulata fuit.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Ah! Sceler oedh y<note n="*" place="margin">Saxon, Schelum.</note> Scholan,</l>
                     <l>O'r Tỽr daflu'r Llyfrau'r tán.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The like poſition have the languages deriving from the <hi>Brittiſh:</hi> as <hi>Jaith Gerniỽ</hi> and <hi>Jaith Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daỽ; i. e.</hi> The <hi>Corniſh</hi> and the <hi>Armoric,</hi> commonly called <hi>Little Brittaine;</hi> which, as Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, was the ancient name of <hi>Ireland.</hi> 
                  <q>Where (ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">In deſcrip. Hyberniae.</note> he) the <hi>Brittſh</hi> language was ſpoken until they were over-run by the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>A verity, which, at my being in that Iſle, I could diſcern more by the names of ſome places there,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121348:36"/>then any thing in the language; excepting only this poſition. The ſaid ſentence being by them thus rendred.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For mach yn gra du S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elki i gamacht gy direcht.</hi> i. e. <hi>Vir bonus ex amore virtutis expreſ è, ſeu ſine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ſe gerit.</hi> The Subſtantive <hi>GRA,</hi> ſo placed, being their <hi>Succedaneum</hi> both of Participle and Gerund.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the variation of the Verb into Gerund and Supine.</head>
               <p>THe Gerund I find with our Author going un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a twofold cognizance: <hi>viz.</hi> In his Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction by name of a voyce belonging to the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive Mood; and in his Inſtitutions by name of participial voyces.</p>
               <p>My apprehenſion is that by his firſt appellation he chiefly meaneth the third Gerund; as by his ſecond he notes the other two; but more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely the middle its ſenſe being clearly partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pial, excelling only in that it relates to the action rather than the perſon acting; whereas the firſt, ſubſtantially, expreſſeth the eſſence of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a middle way between a participle and a Subſtantive; being fortified in its governance according. to the rules of the Genitive of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive, after Adjectives or Subſtantives; as a verbial action proceeding from a Being either <hi>qua</hi> Being, or <hi>qua</hi> ſo qualified: as; <hi>Amor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendi, certuo eundi,</hi> i. e. <hi>Aeneas certus eundi.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:121348:36"/>
               <p>As for our Author's deſign in converting this Gerund to an adjectible ſignification by his <hi>Virgili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Authority of
<q>— Generandi gloria mellis:</q> I muſt ſubmit whether that ſeeming Gerund be other than as one of the participial voices fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. For were it a Gerund, then ſhould it be govern'd as the action of <hi>Gloria;</hi> and muſt alſo govern <hi>mellis</hi> accuſatively. Our Author's own rules teaching that <q>Participles, Gerunds and Supines do govern by ſuch caſes as do the Verbs that they come of.</q> A domination beyond the verge of thoſe participial voices, in regard they denote no time, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Which I inſtance, to eaſe may readers memory from the trouble of conning thoſe many ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives our Author in his Introduction obſerves to require this Gerund inſtead of the infinitive mood. That rule amounting to no more than as if he had ſaid: When ever the eſſence of an action proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as out of the poſſeſſion of a Being, it is more emphatically expreſs'd by this Gerund than either by its Verb, or Subſtantive. <hi>Amor habendi Cecropias apes</hi> ſounding with more vehemency, than either <hi>apes poſsidere,</hi> or <hi>poſſeſsionis apum.</hi> So alſo do we ſay <hi>Otium ſcribcndi literas,</hi> rather than <hi>Scribere, litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſcripturae,</hi> or <hi>Scriptionis;</hi> although the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſeldom expreſs this otherwiſe than by the ſound of the Infinitive Mood.</p>
               <p>Yet ſithence ſometimes, as well as to write, they manifeſt their leiſure of writing. Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to an Engliſh tranſlator, gives an excellent note to this particular, <hi>viz.</hi> that <q>The Engliſh of the Infinitive Mood, or the Participle of the preſent Tenſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121348:37"/>a Subſtantive coming after an Adjective, or Subſtantive which govern a Genitive with the ſign <hi>[of]</hi> is put in the Gerund in <hi>[di].</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And (ſaith he again) <q>The Engliſh of the Participle of the preſent Tence coming without a Subſtantive, and following an Adjective, Verb, or Participle with the ſign <hi>[of]</hi> or any ſign of the Ablative Caſe, is made in the Gerund in <hi>[do]</hi> with or without a Prepoſition.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To which [for I pretend not to much reading; and therefore in rules taken from obſervation, do wholly ſubmit to more literate heads] I only add: That prepoſited ſigns being badges of the vulgari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a language (and therefore induſtriouſly avoided by the Latine,<note place="margin">Part 2. c. 2.</note> as hath been fore-ſhewed) may be ſuſpected to have crept in hither with the familiarity of common converſe. The original Latine deſign, by theſe and the following variation of the Verb ſo meerly tending to the heightening of their Idiome, not probably admitting of ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies.</p>
               <p>And this our Author tacitly obſerves, while for their governance he picketh out Authorities free from thoſe clogs: as,
<q>
                     <l>Efferor ſtudio videndi paren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es.</l>
                     <l>Defeſſus ſum ambulando;</l>
                     <l>Utendum eſt aetate.</l>
                     <l>— Scitatum oracula Phaebi</l>
                     <l>Mittimus —</l>
                  </q> Where the Poet, to avoid the ſaid vulgarity, chooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the voice of a Supine for his expreſſion of a Gerundian ſenſe.</p>
               <p>This third Gerund only tranſcending the Infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Mood by ſtating the cauſe along with the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121348:37"/>which our Author confirms teaching: that, <q>The Engliſh of the Infinitive Mood coming after a reaſon, and ſhewing the cauſe of a reaſon is put in the Gerund in <hi>Dum.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Yet <hi>Scaliger</hi> takes liberty to extend that faculty to the whole three: Saying,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Quoniam cauſam ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundia ſtatuunt, idcirco plus indicant quam verba aut participia;</hi> His end thereby probably being their Paſs under the ſame rationality of appellation. <hi>Gerundia quia rerum gerendarum cauſam unà indicant.</hi> In order whereunto (this compleating the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) what in ſpecial belong'd to it, I conceive, he might lawfully attribute to the whole three, by a <hi>Synechdoche à retrò.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatever may excuſe me for this reduction of our Author's parts of ſpeech: Beſides my igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance why a Gerund ſhould not be accounted a part of ſpeech as well as a Participle: It being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to indicate more; and as well known to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline into, and<note n="*" place="margin">Declinatio eſt Tractio dictionis per caſuum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. So Dr. <hi>Davis.</hi> p. 60.</note> caroch among, its preſcribed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions or Caſes.</p>
               <p>Unleſs that finding both Participle, Gerund and Supine to be but ſo many variations of the word of motion, I may be adjudged pardonable while I ſo comprehend them.</p>
               <p>Concluſively noting, that as this Gerund doth out-do the Infinitive Mood, by ſtating the cauſe along with the action:</p>
               <p>So doth the Supine tranſcend it; Firſt in point of Confidence; and ſecondly, of ſecurity.</p>
               <p>Confidence: In that it expreſſeth future actions as if they were already come to paſs. As when I ſay <hi>Venio ad pagnandum:</hi> I thereby manifeſt a future Tence. But when I expreſs my ſelf by <hi>Pugnatum,</hi> the futurity appeareth ſo certain as p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſent. <hi>Dictum puta</hi> ſaith <hi>Socia</hi> in <hi>Terence.</hi> And rationally, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121348:38"/>all natural motions, the nearer they approach their end or center, move more ſwiftly; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently more vigorouſly. The apprehenſion of which ſtrength muſt neceſſarily introduce confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: and that, ſecurity; as the end or perfection of the motion.</p>
               <p>So that as the firſt Supine intimates the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>in viâ:</hi> the other doth it <hi>in fine. Venio Pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,</hi> expreſſing the buſineſs ſo done, that for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I may reſt ſecurely.</p>
               <p>Wherefore <hi>Scaliger</hi> obſerves how that the Poet deſcribes <hi>Melibaeus</hi> as a perſon ſtrugling with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,<note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>Virgil.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log, 1.</note> and managing his aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irs with more courage than good luck: And <hi>Tylyrus</hi> lying under the ſhade ſupinely.</p>
               <p>Yet he remains diſſatisfied with the <hi>Quare</hi> of the word; ſlighting <hi>Theodors</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as too mean, <hi>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Latinis auribus ſatisfiat:</hi> thoſe are his words.</p>
               <p>My ſenſe is, that a higher reaſon for it is not to be found below the Moon: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifying careleſly or ſecurely, as well as with the face up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. And that poſture naturally following ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as the effect doth the cauſe. Wherefore the muſcle moving the eye upwards Anatomiſts do read <hi>Superbus,</hi> and that in the ſenſe of Noble or Excellent: and but deſervedly; as is eaſily demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable by a Land-skip. I mean, when we view any place with our head between our legs, or otherwiſe inverted. For ſo ſhall we find the appearance of the ſame object <hi>excelling</hi> even to admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Hence comes it that when men have once forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied themſelves with a ſettled fortune of wealth: they naturally look upwards.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman of the firſt head [except while the Spaniard ſwell's in being the ſon of his own
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121348:38"/>right hand] ſeldom known to refuſe the Herauld, more then the Nobles of <hi>Rome</hi> could <hi>Virgil</hi> after he had ſo ſolemnly ſung their extraction from<note n="*" place="margin">Aen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Elyztum:</hi> And <hi>Caeſar's</hi> from the Gods,
<q>—Deus nobis haec otia ſecit.<note place="margin">Eclog. 1.</note>
                  </q> Moſt acceptably compounding the delinquency of that Antonian.</p>
               <p>And thus as ſecurity baniſheth care, doth it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit fanſies reſtinguible in no lower a ſphere.</p>
               <p>A Naturaliſm well known to the Aegyptian; his reprehenſion of the Hebrews importing, They were Idle, Proud, Secure and Careleſs;<note place="margin">Exod. 5.8.</note> therefore they ſaid, <hi>Let us go Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So much for the name and nature of the Supine, which I confeſs doth not ſatisfie our Author's laſt, which follow Adjectives: and he would have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood paſſively Neither know I well how the end of a motion may be ſo rendred. It being analogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal to a Phyſical Ret. And ſay the Metaphyſicks, <hi>Finis &amp; effici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns entitativè ejuſdem ſunt perfectionis.</hi> The only difference being that <hi>Eſſentia eſt quod dat eſſe rei, &amp; eſt primum principinm motus.</hi> So <hi>Jac. Mart. in part Met. Sect.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>Shall we then, with the fore-quoted Phyloſopher,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cal.</hi> ibid. l. 7. c 144.</note> exclude thoſe as being nominals, rather then ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bial Supines? [<hi>Vocatu Druſi,</hi> ſaith he in the ſame place, i. e. <hi>Vocatione: facile expugnatu,</hi> i. e. <hi>expug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione.</hi>] Or may we not rather take them at the rebound? <hi>i. e.</hi> with ſuch motions as in their end meet with reſiſtance and ſo become paſſive? For then the difference will not be great whether we deduce them from the Noune, or the Infinitive Mood of the Verb. The Supine being to the Verb much as is the Adverb to the Noune. Sithence as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121348:39"/>from <hi>Homo</hi> we have <hi>Humanus, Humaniter,</hi> and thence <hi>Humanitas.</hi> So from <hi>voco,</hi> or rather <hi>vocare,</hi> we have <hi>vocand, vocando, vocandum, vocatum, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catu.</hi> Where the motion end's, unleſs we begin again with <hi>vocatio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>vocatu,</hi> in its paſſive reception, ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>vocatio</hi> and <hi>vocari;</hi> [that voice admitting of no Gerund by reaſon of the impoſſibility that I ſhould have more than a gueſs at the cauſe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than proceed from another towards me.] Why may not the motion as well be fanſied to rebound ſo far: eſpecially our Author noting it, <hi>facile factu</hi> or <hi>facile fieri?</hi> Which being but a nicity like the mincing of Cummin attributed of old to <hi>Antonius Pius;</hi> and of ſmall uſe, even by the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines themſelves,<note place="margin">Dion, in Ant. pium.</note> other than to have gradual waies to expreſs the ſame ſenſe by, I ſo paſs.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:121348:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Herm'aelogium;</hi> The fourth PART.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Being a tranſient diſquiſition of the ſtate of our Author's four unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined parts of Speech; with their Concomitant Mutes; and laſtly of the Bronoune.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Author's other four parts of Speech being of the ſame conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as is before expreſſed of his Shapes and Figures:<note place="margin">Part 2. c. 5.</note> I conceive it ſcarce modeſt for a perſon of my ſmall reading, to the ſedulous collections and obſervations of the forecited Gentlemen hereon, toattempt a Supplement. Yet leaſt it be objected that I might by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121348:40"/>have paſſed the Adjective; It, although decline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, of it ſelf ſignifying as little: and therefore as unworthy to bear a part, much leſs a Principle, in ſpeech.</p>
               <p>I muſt add, That notwithſtanding it may juſtly be ſaid of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſung of his uſurped verſes:
<q>Sic vos non vobis—</q> Yet that it is of an intrinſecal conſideration, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing analogical to <hi>Privation:</hi> which is ſuch a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in nature, without which as <hi>MATTER</hi> cannot receive form: So<note n="*" place="margin">Privatio &amp; ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dem ſunt Re &amp; Ratione. See <hi>Com. Magyr.</hi> l. 1. c. 2.</note> Being cannot ſo ſubſiſt. Therefore that <hi>QUALITY,</hi> ſo conſidered, is no way inferiour to <hi>BEING.</hi> But together with it as the ſame *.</p>
               <p>I ſay <hi>together:</hi> as finding the ſeparation, I mean the deciſion of what it is in it ſelf, and what to us, to have puzled as able [though I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I affirm it much as a blind man judging of col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours] a<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> in his Sceptic.</note> Penman as that Age had in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe be only extrinſecal appendants to the firſt mentioned parts or principles of Speech; as meer notes either of their connection, temperament, or circumſtance. And this our Author ſeems to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us of by his calling of them <hi>UNDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLINED.</hi> Declenſion and Riſe in condition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing properly to the Lord,<note place="margin">See his Grammer, p. 261. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and not the Lacquey. Which ſervilety of theirs is further probable, in that the governing power Mr. <hi>Hoole</hi> attributes them is not of themſelves; but of the Being, Motion, or Quality they ſo perſonate or uſher. As is exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary: Firſt by the Adverb; which ſuppoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented in order to this threefold uſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The abbreviation of Sentences.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:121348:40"/>
               <p n="2">2. The gradation of incompatible quantites and qualities. And</p>
               <p n="3">3. A preſcripion to the innumerable circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Action, Time and Place</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the firſt employment I obſerve its note to be ſometimes rude, and ſometimes conformed. Whereof the firſt do notifie things preſent;<note place="margin">(a)</note> (and that commonly with the aſſiſtance of ſome exterior ſign or geſture) and do govern by vertue of the Noune or Verb they ſo obumbrate, as: <hi>En quatuor aras.</hi> That is, <hi>Vide nunc. <hi>Behowld;</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith the Engliſhman.</p>
               <p>But in caſe there be two ſeveral Verbs couched under this note: and that the Verb in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſentence expreſſed be of the ſame ſort with the laſt underſtood; then doth the Adverb govern as by that expreſſed Verb is requireable. For example: <hi>En Priamus, ſunt hìc etiam ſua praemia laudi.</hi> As if he had ſaid, <hi>Vide nunc, Priamus hìc eſt; ſunt hìc etiam ſua praemia laudi.</hi> Whereas if the Verb <hi>ſunt</hi> had been abſent, the expreſſion muſt have been <hi>En Priamum, ſua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> praemia laudi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The word of motion <hi>vide,</hi> in the perſon of the Adverb, there governing: as in the tother the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance proceeds from the Verb of Being.</p>
               <p>Which manifeſts the Adverb to be but a meer ſubſtitute: beſides that <hi>ſic,</hi> and ſuch other Adverbs as have no repreſentative power either of Noune or Verb, dare not aſpire to that eminence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The conformed Adverbs of this uſe are numberleſs, in regard of the nearneſs of this notes relation to the word of Being. But the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance is ever on the ſame account; as, <hi>Pridie Calendarum:</hi> i. e. <hi>Priori die. Calendarum</hi> being there genitively governed as the latter of two Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantives.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121348:41"/>
               <p>Or if I ſay <hi>Pridie calendas.</hi> It will be the ſame as <hi>Dics prae,</hi> or <hi>antc calendas. i. e.</hi> the day juſt or directly before. And therefore is <hi>Calendas</hi> govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accuſatively: the ſtraightneſs of the motion in the ſpace between its extreams being ſo noted by the propoſition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſort of Adverbs are alwaies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed along with the Qualities they ſo explicate; as, <hi>Valde bonus, minis longus, egregie impudens,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore do they not govern at all; the command of the Officer being ſo excluded by the preſence of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The other ſpeciouſly governing Adverbs are generally a ſort of dethroned Adjectives; ſo offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating in order to their like manifeſtation of the accidents of the Verb, as while Adjectives they did of the Subſtantive. And therefore do we ſay <hi>Similis cantus;</hi> but <hi>ſimiliter c. nit;</hi> and doth our Author note that <hi>canit ſimiliter buic; quia</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Dativum adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tunt nominum unde deducta ſunt.</hi> And ſo of the reſt according to the reſpective caſual governance of the Noune or Verb whence they proceed.</p>
               <p>Their pretended governance of Verbs our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor mentions with ſo many <hi>Interdum's</hi> as evinceth its ſubjection to the reaſon of the delivery; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I underſtand his conjunction of ſimilaty and diſſimilary Caſes, Moods and Tenſes other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition I confeſs our Author himſelf ſomewhat ſeemeth to promote to a governing ſtate, while he teacheth that <hi>Praepoſitioni accidit caſuum regimen;</hi> but he adds, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve conſtructio.</hi> As it he had ſaid, <hi>Earum regimen, ſi vis, conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. e. <hi>orationis ſtructuram appelles.</hi> That being the end of their poſition before other
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121348:41"/>parts, as hath been fore-ſhewed:<note place="margin">Part 2. c. 2.</note> And [that I may not ſeem either to expound our Author, or contradict ſuch as poſitively affirm the ſaid gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance altogether on my ſcore] I find tacitly rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by my fore-quoted Countrey-man <hi>Joannes Davidas Rhaeſus</hi> [known in <hi>England</hi> by name of Doctor <hi>Davies;</hi> and in <hi>Italy</hi> by a Tract he there writ in the <hi>Florentine</hi> Idiome <hi>de ſtructu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>á Latini Sermonis</hi>] who in his <hi>Inſtitutiones Cym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aecae,</hi> or Latine Welſh-Grammer, where he mentions theſe governances, hath no ſuch word as <hi>Regunt;</hi> but <hi>nectuntur, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctunt, ſerviunt;</hi> reſpectively diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Adverb, Conjunction and Prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The ſame I alſo find in Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s, viz. The firſt joyned, the ſecond joyning, and the third ſerving.</p>
               <p>As for the Interjection: To aſcribe it a regular governance, were to confound it with a <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis.</hi> And therefore doth our Author note it <hi>ad Placitum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O foſtus dies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O fortuna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>os nimium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O formoſe puer,</hi> &amp;c</p>
               <p>It rather governing its concomitant Mute; and ſo from an imperfect, ſcarce worded, voice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the moſt abſolute ornament of Speech.</p>
               <p>As thoſe who have received their education from the ſedulous Lectures of Academick Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors can amply witneſs: And recommend as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ingenious conſideration, and publick. Were not theſe geſtures in moſt Countries ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; and therefore beſt attainable by obſervation of their attractive effect on the attention of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Auditories.</p>
               <p>As I remember once merrily hinted at by a no leſs grave than ingenions Preachet in <hi>Leyden;</hi> who
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121348:42"/>to ſatisfie the importunity of a young Divine of his acquaintance, having lent him an elaborate and, in that very place, often approved Sermon to be delivered by this Candidate In order to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the Paſtorſhip, but not taking, had no ſhift to diſabuſe my new Levite, other than by perſwading him That the fault lay in his own for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs, that he had not borrowed his Bow as well as his Fidle. Both, indeed, proceeding from the ſame root: As may be inſtanced by a Bowler. Whom we ſhall ever ſee ſhouldering, puffing, ſtamping, or drawing back, as the condition of his caſt ſeems devious.</p>
               <p>But if he finds it equally running its right mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ground: Then, he either directly followeth, or ſtedfaſtly look's on, as in his poſture of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
               <p>That theſe Geſtures (though accompany'd with, or proceeding from, never ſo ſtrong incina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of an unfaſcinating mind) can either take from, add to, or otherwiſe direct the motion once paſſed the Gameſters hand, I ſhall not ſuſpect.</p>
               <p>Yet having often laugh'd at them in others, and endeavour'd to forbear them my ſelf, but with more i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kſomneſs than ſucceſs, I cannot but think them natural.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially while I obſerve the ſame, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, to hold with the Orator. And that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the perfection of his language. Which as it doth leaſt multiply its attendants with theſe notes, or (that I may not cauſleſly vary from our Authors language) parts of Speech; ſo requireth is fewer outward ſigns for its ornament. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: The Latine Adverbial note <hi>Olim,</hi> ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a raſſed as well as future time. The note <hi>cum,</hi> uſed both fo an Adverb, Conjunction and Prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121348:42"/>As it ſerves either to declare the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Verb; to joyn ſentences; or elſe as a prepoſited badge to the Ablative caſe of a word of Being. Whereas in vulgar languages its ſenſe is expreſſed by notes ſeverally differing according to the ſaid reſpective imployments.</p>
               <p>And hence probably comes it that the Spaniſh Reel or French Shrugge be not yet faſhonable among the Italians: whoſe diſcourſes they render no leſs magnetick by the interjection of certain nodds, ſtops, and change of countenance; which, the word Bluſh being too young, I want expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for;<note place="margin">The Flavour is ſtill the Flavour.</note> Other than (as we ſay of the Flavour of Wine) that they are becoming the gravity of an Italian.</p>
               <p>Whether there be any Books writ on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, I am not certain. But obſerve that, before the uſe of Bandſtrings, this gravity hath been emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the Engliſh. The noble <hi>Chaucer,</hi> as he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiat's the deportment of the Arabian Envoy in the Tartarian preſence; thus ſinging;
<q>
                     <l>Accordant to his woords was his chere;<note place="margin">The Squier Tale</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As teacheth art of ſpeech hem that it lere.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:121348:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the Pronoune with the Arts from it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</head>
               <p>I Conclude with the note of the Nodd the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune: which our Author calls A part of Speech much like to, and indeed is the ſame with a Noune; although it differeth from his Noune Adjective in that it denotes a perſonal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and from his Subſtantive, firſt in reſpect that this perſonality is neither proper nor appellative: and ſecondly, in that it imply's number: <hi>I, THOU</hi> and <hi>H E.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Under which be comprehended the other twelve: and to whom is added the officious Relative, as the Gentleman <hi>Ipocrifat</hi> in Herauldrie.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Wherefore our Author adds that it is uſed in ſhewing or rehearſing.</q> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> The Pronoune in ſhewing: as, <hi>I love:</hi> and the Relative in rehearſing: as, <hi>I who love.</hi>
                  <q>Ille ego qui quondam —</q> Which alſo is the office of its Verb And that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in order to its own being; or Paſſions; as, <hi>I am,</hi> or <hi>I am called upon;</hi> or elſe in order to its perſonal poſture: as, <hi>I ſit,</hi> or <hi>ſleep.</hi> All which muſt have the caſual word nominatively placed, becauſe the motion terminates in it ſelf: And ſo remain's a monument of the primitive unity.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:121348:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I, THOU,</hi> and <hi>HE</hi> living as one, until they came to diſtinguiſh <hi>MINE, THINE</hi> and <hi>HIS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe introduc'd Trade; and that the multiplicity of clinſhing words and, tropical ſentences in order to perſwaſion. Inſomuch that ſuch is the preſent excellency of that Art: as it might be taken for no Paradox (ſaving the gravity of a<note n="*" place="margin">Qui ratio naliterutitur argumentis ad perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris nomen meruit eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi non perſuaſerit. <hi>Quint.</hi>
                  </note> Qu ntili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſt) from the young O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ator while he maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moneys he had promiſed his Tutor for teaching him the whole Art of Rhetorick were not due, until he could, by that Art, perſwade him to part with the ſumme he neither yet had, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for him when he had it And that, he muſt expect, would create a diſpute. <hi>Mercurie</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his altitude until he doth <hi>Iater duos lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes media currere ut Logicè reciprocetur oratio</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">N. Comes.</note>. An Art whoſe Circumſtantials the experience of my ſhort ſtep of travel could not obſerve ſo long d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elt upon beyond the Seas, as in the Engliſh Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities is uſual. And therefore cannot ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applaud the Epitome given it by my moſt worthily honoured friend Sir <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nelme Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In Treat. of Bodies. part. 2. c. 3.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n argument (ſaith he) The aſſumed Term, unto which the other two are enterchangeably joyn'd, is either ſaid of them or they are ſaid of it. And from hence do ſpring three different kinds of Syllogiſm. For either the aſſumed or middle term is ſaid of both the other two: or both they are ſaid of it: or it is ſaid of one of them, and the other is ſaid of it. And this is the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteric of the three Figures our Clerks ſo much talk of.</q> Which (having elſewhere occaſionally cleared the Mathematical Spring of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>) I
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121348:44"/>here mention, to manifeſt how that thoſe ſeven that the civilized part of the world do honour with the Epithite of Gent: or Liberal be no other than Grammer expanded. And ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the uſe of this its preſent Reduction.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:121348:44"/>
            <head>The Uſe of the whole TREATISE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Text ſaith; <q>There are three that bear witneſs in heaven? The Father, the Word,<note place="margin">Joh. Ep. I. 5.7.</note> and the Holy Ghoſt; and theſe three are one. There are three that bear witneſs in earth; the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the Water, and the Blood; and theſe three agree in one.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As I am no quarreller at Scripture; ſo am I not certain whether the Original ſounds <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. However, both coming from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Spiro.</note> had the more ſtrict preſent occaſion of the Evangeliſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Tranſlators to have expreſſed the <hi>Blood</hi> by name of <hi>Winde,</hi> they had thereby ſaved me the uſe of faith; ſithence I ſhould then have underſtood the aſſertion Philoſophically; as knowing the water, wind and Spirit to be one, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Submiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Religioni Philoſoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, clavibus ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſus legitim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> utamini. <hi>Verul. ad. Acad. Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabrig.</hi>
               </note> The wind a rarified water, and the Spirit a rarified wind. And conſequently, the wind to be a coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated ſpirit, and the water a coagulated winde. So bearing their witneſs of the infiniteneſs of the opening and the ſhutting:
<q>Mens agitans molem, &amp; coeco ſe corpore miſcens.</q>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:121348:45"/>As the <hi>Maronian</hi> in the fourth of his <hi>Georgicks</hi> hath it;<note place="margin">See the laſt Embleme.</note> (probably) out of <hi>Thales Mileſius,</hi> whoſe ſenſe <hi>Cicero</hi> in his books <hi>De Natnrâ Deorum</hi> ſo much depends on; and we find abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the twelfth chapter of that admirable Book of <hi>Job;</hi> and elſewhere throughout the Text.</p>
            <p>My intent hence is not, with<note n="*" place="margin">In Relig. med.</note> Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> to maintain a multiplicity of worlds. But to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce firſt how <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> principles of the world do bear the ſame witneſs. Form being no other then a vivified matter, as proportionated Beings be the <hi>au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>optic</hi> gallantry of that Form formed; and wherein the reſpective decay of heat is the receſs of the life towards its abſcondity. So ſecondly (the excellency of the microcoſme conſiſting in its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſive faculty,<note place="margin">Plato in Timan.</note> as the manifeſted expanſion of the unity of mans ſoul to its trine) How it muſt alſo in its Philoſophie bear a like teſtimony. The word of motion being a word of Being actuated; as <hi>amare</hi> is a word eſſentially declaring the action of <hi>Amor;</hi> and modable according to the temporal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the lover towards whatever Being he therein can fanſie perfection.</p>
            <p>Whence the Ancients fained <hi>Cupid</hi> in as many ſhapes as they do <hi>Venus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme.</note> or (as <hi>Pauſanias</hi> latinized hath it) <hi>Tot amores quot Veneres.</hi> Yet they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized all under Greatneſs and Goodneſs: which, as ſaith the ſame Author, are but one; <hi>Quia iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidem appetitum alliciunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And its obſervable that the perfection towards which a motion is thus directed or attracted is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten inviſible, even as is the fire in water; yet known to be there by reaſon of its flowing. For when the ambient cold ſorceth the fire to its center; the water, as it ceaſeth its flowing, is no
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121348:45"/>more water, but ice; until the fire be invited to its priſtine expanſion by exterior warmth.</p>
            <p>Even ſo, in what ever, whether viſible or inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, quality of a Being my opinion fanfieth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; this perfection but ſo thence vaniſhing, the motion of my love immediately retires to its firſt eſſentiality.</p>
            <p>And thus as <hi>John</hi> loveth or not loveth <hi>Joan,</hi> be the cogitations of man expreſſible by the ſaid<note n="*" place="margin">Intelligete, movere, &amp; generare eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentialiter idem ſunt. <hi>See D. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſon in Currie. Chymic. part 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>TRINE-U NE</hi> words occaſionally varyed and attended as in this Treatiſe I have aſſayed to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. So that I can at preſent think of no remaining intricacie ſaving when, in order to a more copious or conciſe delivery, I am induced to compound the <hi>termini</hi> of a ſentence ſome or one of them; which conjoyned branches, although they contain a Verb reſpectively in themſelves, do yet amount to no more than either a Suppoſition, Declaration, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereof the firſt is known by its prepoſited note of doubt; as when, with our Author, I ſay: <hi>Si cupis placere magiſtro utere diligentiâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond by its ſubjoyning office, as to ſay; <hi>ut placeas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third by the Relative; as <hi>Qui cupis placere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And the fourth by the abſence of a Verb otherwiſe than infinitively poſited. As if I were to ſay <hi>Cupiens placere magiſtro utere diligentiâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all which the underſtood Noun Perſonal or Pronoun <hi>[Tu]</hi> muſt be the Being whence the Verb <hi>utere</hi> moveth towards <hi>diligentia</hi> as the word ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating the ſentence. And the governance is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral in regard the Verb m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>veth not as attracted by it, but as a mode of pleaſing the Maſter. See <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:121348:46"/>
            <p>Yet that what hath been ſaid may be made more ſupplemental to our Author, I ſhall further partize his Example, after the uſual Pedagogick manner, ſuppoſing my ſelf a Pupil queſtioned by my Tutor what part of Speech is ſupplyed by the word <hi>Cupis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Verbial part.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How know you it to be a Verb?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that it is a word of motion; that is, moving between the deſiring and the deſired Being.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What kind of Verb is it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that it moveth from the ſaid underſtood Pronoun (which is its material cauſe) ſimply to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its formal: It is a Verb Active. But, that I offend not my more curious Grammarian, I muſt alſo call it a Verb Neuter; in regard forſooth we do not read <hi>Cupior.</hi> Although the <hi>Engliſh</hi> love as well to be deſired.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>After what Conjugation do you decline it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The fourth. And the reaſon therefore ſee in <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What part of speech is</hi> Magiſtro?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Noun Subſtantive.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know you it to be a Noun Subſtantive?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that it manifeſts a Being; ſee <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How do you articulate it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the Maſculine Gender.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In regard it denotes Rule, which neceſſarily implyeth Action See <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Aſter which of our Authors rules is it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe that whether I take the word from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which jumps with the <hi>French</hi> Idiome
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121348:46"/>thrice more; or from <hi>magis</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> greater in ſtation; It followeth that it be declined after the moſt honourable way incident to its termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Would you hence infer that ſuch words termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating in</hi> [er] <hi>as carry the more honourable<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be declin'd after this ſecond Rule, and the leſs worthy after the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I thought you had been thereof already ſo ſatisfied in <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. that to urge me here to reaffirm it were impertinent.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But how comes it then to paſs that</hi> Puer <hi>is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined after this, and</hi> Pater <hi>after that; ſithence it's paſs'd queſtion but the laſt is more honourable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I confeſs it <hi>quoad hominem;</hi> but not <hi>quoad naturam:</hi> For, Propagation being the eternizor of nature, Naturaliſts do deſervedly ſtate it as the chief of mans life. Therefore doth love follow the off-ſpring; and are the ſteps from the womb to the wedding more honorable than thoſe between it and the reduction of the Creature; and that by ſo much as life is more deſirable then death. Whence I conclude that ſuch Maſculines terminating in <hi>[er]</hi> as on the wheel of life be placed between the ſtate and the end are naturally declinable rather after the third rule. I will not ſay alwayes declined; for that (as one notes) <hi>Sermo Inter agreſtiaing ma pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ortus doctiorum legibus aliquand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> refragatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What caſe conceive you</hi> Magiſtro <hi>there to ſtand in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Dative.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it ſtands governed by the acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively poſited Verb <hi>Placere.</hi> See <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How cometh</hi> Magiſtro <hi>to be gover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d by the Infinitive Mood</hi> placere, <hi>it to me ſeeming but us only
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121348:47"/>joyned with it, by way of appoſition, to make up the word of ſenſe; This anſwering the</hi> (whom) <hi>as the other doth the</hi> (what)?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our Author doth not tell us that the caſual word muſt anſwer the queſtions whom and what; but whom or what; <q>and that the word that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth next the Verb as anſwering to either of thoſe, is (ſaving his exceptions) the caſual;</q> which therefore is here due to <hi>Placere,</hi> as ſo anſwering the queſtion. Deſire what? To pleaſe. To pleaſe whom? The Maſter. So that <hi>Magiſtro</hi> comes hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not by appoſition; but as a word governed of <hi>placere.</hi> The Infinitive Mood, when ſo ſerving, no way quitting its governing prerogative more than doth a Participle or Gerund. I ſay ſo ſerving; for that as <hi>To pleaſe</hi> by anſwering the queſtion (whom) becomes as a caſual word; and a word of ſenſe as it denotes a perfection wanted by the placitor<note n="*" place="margin">Part. 2. c. 4.</note>: <hi>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> COVETEST TO PLEASE</hi> ſo making up a compleat ſentence. Even ſo, when I thus particularlize this pleaſing, doth the ſenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a Reaſon; as hath been fore-proved by our Authors Ovidian Authority cited, <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. where the firſt and third words add nothing to the Reaſon; only encomiate the quality of Arts, and expreſs a neceſſity of fixation in the learner. So that it were the ſame if I ſaid <hi>Placere magiſtro requirit diligentiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Suppoſe you were to expreſs</hi> placere <hi>by an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntial word of Senſe; as to ſay: If thou covet the pleaſure or delight of the Maſter. How would you latinize it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Si cupis delectamentum Magiſtri.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what caſe woud you conceive the word</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectamentum, <hi>ſo placed, to ſtand in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Accuſative.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121348:47"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>And why?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As governed by the Verb Tranſitive <hi>Cupis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know you</hi> Cupis <hi>to be a Verb Tranſitive?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it anſwereth all the expectations of that Verb manifeſted, <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. It being none of thoſe motions of deſign; but a down right natural one, as <hi>Amo;</hi> whether we take the word from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o,</hi> or <hi>à cupidine amoris;</hi> as Mr. <hi>Holyoake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Admit you were to define this ſuppoſition by one word; as of the Reaſon hath been fore-noted in</hi> Part. 1. c. 1. <hi>How would you expreſs your ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Obſequens utitur</hi> or (to continue the firſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative mode of ſpeech) <hi>Tu obſequens utere diligentiâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>By name of what part of speech would you call</hi> Obſequens <hi>ſo placed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Properly by neither of our Authors eight. It there being only a participial voice, or (as Mr. <hi>Hoole</hi> would have it) Noun, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. A Participle ſignifying no time; and therefore governing no otherwiſe than as a Noun Adjective. As in <hi>Part</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. hath been foreſhewed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeding with our Authors example where he adds</hi> Nec ſis tantus ceſſator ut calcaribus indigeas: <hi>I would in the firſt place know w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at part of speech is</hi> Nec?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Conjunction coupling the foregoing and following clauſes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What part of ſpeech is</hi> Ceſſator.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Noun Subſtantive or word of Being.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it declined?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Maſculinely aſter our Authors third rule.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why Maſculinely?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In regard the very being Slugge denotes action: as we uſe to ſay; Its better be idle then do nothing. See <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is it declined after the third rule?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:121348:48"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By reaſon of its termination; as hath been ſhewed, <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>what condition or caſe doth it here ſtand in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Nominative.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth it ſo govern the Verb</hi> Sis, <hi>or is it governed by it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is governed by it; and yet cannot proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called a word of Senſe in regard of its fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Conjunction.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>From what being then doth</hi> Sis <hi>move towards</hi> Ceſſator?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From the Pronoun <hi>Tu;</hi> which is underſtood as couched under the perſonality of the Verb. See <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. and <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If</hi> Ceſſator <hi>ſtands here as a word governed, why doth it not decline its Nominative condition or caſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By reaſon that the motion governing is a Verb of Being, See <hi>Part.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What part of speech is</hi> Tantus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Noun Adjective, or word of Quality.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How cometh it to be underſtood as a Quality, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hence it denotes Magnitude, and not Bonitude?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The identity of quantity and quality hath been already ſhewed, <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3 But for your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfaction know that (the ſlothful being concluded vitious) its quantitative ſignification implyeth ſo much of evil; as to ſay <hi>Tantum</hi> or <hi>tam magnum vitium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whnt Caſe, Gender and Number doth it ſtand in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> The Nominative Caſe, Maſculine Gender, and ſingular Number.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that it is here adjected to <hi>Ceſſator;</hi> which is a word of Being at preſent, ſo affected, See <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:121348:48"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What part of speech it ut?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Conjunction cauſal joyning <hi>Calcaribus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeas</hi> to the ſubjunctive declaration foregoing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why call you it not a Sentence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the preſence of the Conjunction ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it ſubordinate to another leſs clogged Clauſe or Sentence; as to ſay <hi>ut calcaribus indigeas utere diligentiâ.</hi> Whence if I take off <hi>ut,</hi> and ſo deliver my ſelf definitively, the firſt will be a compleat ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as well as the laſt. As to ſay: <hi>Ego ſum ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> or <hi>Ego calcaribus indigeo; tu uteris or utere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentiâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Might not theſe be joyned by</hi> Quòd <hi>aſwell as</hi> Ut; <hi>It alſo being a Conjunction cauſal, and giving the ſame Engliſh ſound?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The deſign of avoiding a multiplicity of theſe Attendants hath been throughout this Tract ſo canvaſſed, that to find them retained by any recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation below a preciſe neceſſity, or being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to be miſtaken <hi>Dick</hi> for <hi>Robin,</hi> were to eſpie a contradiction inconſiſtent with the <hi>Roman</hi> inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity. Which induceth me to obſerve that Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences thus joyned neceſſarily implying one of the formal differences of time mentioned. <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. do require their Conjunction by notes moſt ſutable to that time. And therefore to joyn a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity by a note ſounding ſo neer the Relative as <hi>Quod,</hi> were ſuch a piece of vulgarity as would ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the expreſſion to be ſcarce <hi>Latine</hi> ſenſe. A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation being ever underſtood of things or actions paſs'd, the preſent being no ſooner mentioned than paſſed. And that therefore the <hi>Latines</hi> by <hi>Quòd</hi> do joyn ſuch ſentences only as imply a paſt or preſent tenſe, as they do thoſe that ſpeak a futurity by <hi>ut;</hi> it ſounding ſo near the wiſhing Adverb <hi>Utinam</hi> As in this particular <hi>Ut calcaribus indigeas;</hi> where the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121348:49"/>Verb potentially moded manifeſteth a future need by voyce of the preſent Tenſe. See <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>All which our Author teacheth ſhowing that the reduction of the Infinitive Mood by <hi>Quòd</hi> and <hi>Ut,</hi> muſt be preciſely <hi>in hunc modum;</hi> viz. <hi>Quòd tu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſti incolumis gaudeo. ut tu fabulam agas volo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where I break up School; wiſhing ſome through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enabled linguiſt would ſo <hi>fabulam agere,</hi> that mankind might as no longer ſpeak as Parats; So not want the fruition of thoſe other advantages in the altitude of ſuch a <hi>Venus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verulam,</hi> ibid. p. 261.</note> of <hi>Apelles</hi> ſuppoſed le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible by the noble <hi>Origin</hi> of this Eſſay; which therefore I Corollarily proſtrate envelloped by the following Embleme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121348:49"/>
            <figure>
               <head>The Repreſentors are
<list>
                     <item>1 Caelus or Perfection.</item>
                     <item>2 Saturn or Beings.</item>
                     <item>3 Cupid in Mercuries diſguiſe.</item>
                     <item>4 Venus Popularis.</item>
                     <item>5 Venus hortenſis.</item>
                     <item>6 Venator.</item>
                     <item>7 Venus Terreſtris.</item>
                     <item>8 Venus Caeleſtis.</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:121348:50"/>
            <head>The Huntſman Speaks!</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>AS I was winding of my morning Call,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Whether I ſtrain'd beyond my uſual</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Force I not well remember) Such a fright</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Invaded me when I me ſaw (poor wight)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſſociated and compaſs'd as you ſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſtun'd I ſtood; till viewing <hi>Mercury</hi>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus placed in the round I to him ſaid:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Son of great</hi> Jove! <hi>my Guide to whom are paid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My conſtant vows: and to whoſe flying fame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be Sacrific'd the</hi> (a) <hi>Tongues of all the Game</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ever yet in foreſt wild I ſlew:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vouchſafe the meaning of this enterveiw</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To thy aſtoniſh'd Suppliant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>—Which Prayer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſon of</hi> Main (B) <hi>hovering in the Air,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus anſwered. —</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>— Courage Woodman! for this ſhall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Create thee no more trouble than thy call.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Scheme</hi> (C) <hi>erected being by the Art</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of thy King</hi> Saturn's (D) <hi>Son; who make'ſt his part,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus to detect what the enſuing fate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall be 'oth' Roman Tongue as well as (E) State.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>(a)</hi> The Tongues of all Sacrifices the Ancients of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Mercury; as God not only of Speech, but alſo of Reaſon and Prudence. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the Woodman, on this occaſion, chooſe him for his chief rather then <hi>Diana.</hi> See <hi>Nat. Com. Mytholog.</hi> l. 5.</p>
            <p>(B) <hi>Maia</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Atlas</hi> and <hi>Pleion:</hi> A Nymph on whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> begat <hi>Mercurie.</hi> See <hi>Virgil Aeneid.</hi> 8.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:121348:50"/>
            <p>(C) Or Hieroglyphick <hi>Schaema.</hi> i. e. <hi>Orationis exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na pars &amp; dignitas. H. O.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(D) <hi>Picus</hi> moſt skilfull in Augurie, and therefore fain'd transformed to a Wood-pecker. <hi>Ovid. Met.</hi> 14. Although by the word <hi>Augurium</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> underſtood not only the divination particularly taken from the chattering of birds, but alſo from all other obſervable cauſes or Oſtents whatſoever appearing in Heaven, Air, or Earth; as affirmeth <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> and out of him <hi>Gasper Peucerus in l. de Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis, pag.</hi> 374.</p>
            <p>(E) That is, how the ſtate of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from its golden condition in the ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Provincial Potentates. Who, ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their particular more then the publick wellfare, ſhall ſubject it to want; whoſe very apprehenſion as it uſhers all kinds of ſelfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo ſhall be multiplyed the Mode and Caſes of the language. The firſt being Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally but one, as hath been already ſhewed <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. And the ſecond but two, <hi>viz.</hi> The Nominative and the Accuſative, that is, The condition of a ſubſtantial Being whence the motion taketh its riſe, and of the qualified Being towards which it formally tendeth.</p>
            <p>The Vocative being comprehenſible under the Nominative, as only diſtinguiſhable by our poſition of the perſon in the arrear of the Verb, and the riſe of our voyce in the cloſe of the period. Or elſe of this Additional note of the Writer[?], and the oblique caſes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the reſpective indirect motions of the Verb, ſince invented, as by the diviſion of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is here repreſented.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:121348:51"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wherefore bright</hi> (F) CAELUS <hi>over</hi> Saturns <hi>face</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Having the curtain drawn reſumes his place.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſhew Perfection beneath the skie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henceforth to ſeek ſhall be a vanitie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Save what weak loves by their deſcent retain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>On ſelf-deſign; (which therefore Poets fain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From th' loins of</hi> CAELUS <hi>in the</hi> (G) <hi>third degree</hi>)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At which in them to aim this Dietie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> SATURNS <hi>boſom leaves the purblind</hi> (H) <hi>spark.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Opinionately roving at his mark.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>(F) By others call'd <hi>CAELIUS</hi> ſon of the Skie and Day; for his excelling and permanent beauty ſtyled Perfection. <hi>Bonum</hi> and <hi>Pulchrum</hi> being convertible; as hath been fore ſhewed. And that theſe qualities were in him perfect, is manifeſt in that from him the Heavens were called <hi>Caeli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was father to <hi>SATURN</hi> who was God of Plenty; whence his Age might be called <hi>Golden.</hi> His name alſo coming <hi>a Satu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando,</hi> aſwell as from the Hebrew <hi>SATAR. i. e. To hide</hi> or ſhut up; both typifying the witneſſed in the Philoſophical uſe of this Tract forementioned. See more of his golden age in <hi>Fulgentius</hi> his Mythologie; as of his veil and ſucceſſion in Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh's</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoric of the World, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>(G) <hi>VENUS</hi> being daughter to <hi>JUPITER</hi> ſon of <hi>SATURN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(H) <hi>CUPID</hi> ſuppo'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d originally blinded with <hi>Saturns</hi> veil, and therefore ſhooting rovingly as his fanſie ſhall occaſionally incite him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards either <hi>VEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſhoots <hi>Saturns</hi> arrows, as perſonating the word of motion conveying the indigent
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121348:51"/>deſires of the word of Being towards its formal cauſe or word of ſenſe here repreſented by <hi>VEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> Wherefore alſo he ſtands in <hi>MERC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIES's</hi> diſguiſe: <hi>SAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN MERC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY</hi> and <hi>VEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> now figuring the remnant of that wiſdom which before the veyling was ſpecified by <hi>Celius, Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mercurie;</hi> As averreth <hi>Triſmegiſtus.</hi> Neither could <hi>Mercurie</hi> repreſent theſe ſeveral moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his own perſon, he being no Archer.</p>
            <p>If any then be ſo critical as to queſtion how I dare add arrows to <hi>Saturn:</hi> I wiſh he would conceive them to be thoſe which, erſt, <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> having ſtoln from <hi>Apollo,</hi> hid here under <hi>Saturns</hi> veryl for the preſent uſe of <hi>Cupid;</hi> and ſo paſs my application with the ſame face that <hi>HORACE</hi> obſerves <hi>PHAEB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> to have done the theft:
<q>
                  <l>Te, boves olìm niſi redidiſſes</l>
                  <l>Per dolum amotos, Puerum minaci</l>
                  <l>Voce dum terret, viduus Pharetrâ,</l>
                  <l>— Riſit Apollo, <hi>l. 1. Od 10.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which alſo ſhews there ſhall in</hi> SATURNS <hi>ſtate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Provincial Kings ſucceed; whoſe love and hate;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Both politick and corporal ſhall be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Guided alone by ſelf-conveniencie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then may you hear Romes Counſl'ar</hi> (I) <hi>Orator</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perſwading theſe four</hi> Venus's <hi>to' adore.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which I forbear to blazon; ſince (Sans doubt)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When by ſuch means your ſtate is come about,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Through various fortunes) from the Sheephook to</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Crozier; <hi>they will be ſo known that ſo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The world ſhall ſpeak their language.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:121348:52"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>— what to make</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet of this tail devouring heaſt the Snake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Other then as it the viciſſitude</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of time and things denotes, I not conclude.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Though when the Crozier is outwor'n of all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Its idolized fukes Canonical,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some think things ſhall again turn Saturnine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But that conceipt I paſs to my Divine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>(I) <hi>Cicero</hi> who in his third book <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Naturâ Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> mentioneth four <hi>Venus's.</hi> Three whereof I find ſitnamed by <hi>Nat. Comes Mytholog. l.</hi> 4. <hi>viz. Caeleſtis, Hortenſis</hi> and <hi>Popularis.</hi> The firſt of which typifying the word of ſenſe anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the direct natural motion of the Verb, I have here plac'd as the Accuſative caſe of the Noun. The ſecond as figuring poſſeſſion, and conſequently anſwering the circular motion, I have marſhall'd Genitively. The third, as carrying an analogie with <hi>Romes</hi> Political confederacy, I have ſeated Ablatively. And laſtly, <hi>Cicero's</hi> fourth (which I conceive to be <hi>Venus terreſtris,</hi> and ſo the end of Acquiſition) I have ranked Datively.</p>
            <p>For which reaſons I further diſtinguiſh the firſt by its natural amorous aſpect no way diverted by imployment. The ſecond by the Spindle. The third by the Silkworms; and the fourth by the Cyphon. That ſo they might diſtinctly repreſent the four re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective motions of the Verb in the ſecond Chapter of the ſecond Part of this Diſcourſe already mentioned.</p>
            <p>As for the Vocative Condition of the Noun: Its incapacity of receiving any ſhot of <hi>Cupid</hi>'s invited
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121348:52"/>me to repreſent it by a Huntſman. Whom a ſight ſo reſembling the<note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Sands</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem before <hi>Ovid Met.</hi> 30</note> Gargaphian might terrifie to a religious compellation of his <hi>Genius</hi> thus to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate.</p>
            <q>
               <l>And Reader! now (though Caelus be aſcended)</l>
               <l>If thou but fain our <hi>Venus</hi>'s contracted;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Cupid's</hi> ſeat to <hi>Mercurie</hi> reſigned,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Analogie</hi> will ſoon appear compleated.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Matter</cell>
                        <cell>Beinge</cell>
                        <cell>Saturne</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>forme</cell>
                        <cell>Motion</cell>
                        <cell>Mercuri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Priuation or Proportion</cell>
                        <cell>Quality</cell>
                        <cell>Venus</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>The Antients as when diſtinguiſhing between ſpiritual and corporeal nature they likened the one to a Trine and the other to a ſquare; So did they typifie the whole by water. Finding it, as in its orbicular form to be the Trine of a ſquare; So in its ſubſtance or entity to contain the Fire, Love or Life of all Beings; like as the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians Center doth his Lines.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:121348:53"/>
            <p>This fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Greek Philoſophers called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> The mind [or rather mental motion; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>mente agito</hi>] And the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Divines <hi>ELOHIM,</hi> which our vulgar tranſlation engliſheth <hi>God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Vpon the face of the waters</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>moved the Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom alone in his trin-unity won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful be the glory for ever.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:121348:53"/>
            <head>Rectori magnifico &amp; Profeſſoribus in almâ matre inclytâ Friſiorum Academiâ quae eſt Franequerae S.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ractatulum hunc relegenti confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia mihi occurrit de communi librorum fato <hi>Cenſurâ.</hi> Quae quanquam ut cerebri anfractus variegata ſit: interim tamen (dum Vota nihil definiant) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſario, quoad hoc, reducibilis videbam in quid unum: Num ſcil. Philoſopho, an cum ratione inſanienti potius quadret. Quapropter, &amp; quum judicium omne plenam ſupponit judicandi cognitionem, exſeminariò rem diſſecandam cenſui: Alſtedio tradente modum.</p>
            <p>
               <q>In omni diſciplinâ (inquit<note n="*" place="margin">In ency. clopaed. Philoſoph. l. 4.</note> ill:) oportet ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare primò <hi>Cur:</hi>
               </q> &amp; ſecundo <hi>Quomodo</hi> ſit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenda. <hi>i. e.</hi> Finis &amp; modus ad finem tendens.</p>
            <p>Finis hujus ex libri epigraphe patet ut ſit <hi>Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis rationalitas.</hi> Conamen quod, dum incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum reſtat, duo imprimis conſideranda praebet: <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilitatem</hi> ſcil. &amp; <hi>Poſſibilitatem</hi> rei.</p>
            <p>Prior ex <hi>Ariſtotele</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfirmari eſt, ubi docet <q>In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eligendis quàm detrahere oportet eligendorum
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121348:54"/>excellentiam.<note place="margin">Topic. l. 3. Tract, 2. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Quia ſi honore dignius eſt optabilius; etiam id quod honore eſt dignum eſt optabile.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Sic enim ſi per cauſas ſcire praeſtat quàm per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, (quod ex Scientiae definitione patet) etiam rationalis Grammatices authoritativae ut praeſtet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt; &amp; per conſequens, quod optabile quid talis ſit. Quia quin ars Grammaticalis eſt honore digna Credo neminem inficias ire, vel exinde quo inter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem &amp; belluam diſtinguit.</p>
            <p>Ratificatam invenio Poſteriorem per Praenobilem <hi>Franciſcum</hi> de <hi>Verulam:</hi> Heroen in omni Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiae genere e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imiè agnitum.<note place="margin">Tom. 6. cap. 1.</note> Qui in <hi>magnâ</hi> ſua <hi>Scientiarum Inſtauratione</hi> (libro per Europam uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> adeò celebrato ut veſtrâ quin in Bibliothecâ locum tenet nil moror) non ſolum aſſerit Artem Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticalem poſſe reddi Philoſophicam: ſed &amp; ipſummet Grammaticen quandam mente ſibi tenuiſſe conceptam, <q>quae non verborum cum verbis, ſed cum rebus ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logian monſtraret.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hocque (Excellentiſsimi viri) lucubratiunculic hiſce m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ortum dedit. Id enim cum legeram, mihi potenter aurem vellere fateor. ut qui Romanâ in lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guâ (omniferae doctrinae Brittano maximè neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ) per noſtratis <hi>Lelii</hi> Grammaticen è pucritiâ dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat inſtructus fueram. Donec paulò ante deſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam peregrinationem, cum Nobilibus quibuſdam tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marinis, tunc temporis Oxoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commorantibus, memet affociando, ea mihi familiaris facta eſt, ut antea, eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſolo converſationis medio, Anglicana fuerat. Aliâ de loquendi ratione ut prius ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iarem tam procul aberat.</p>
            <p>Illiuc verò quaſi experrectus: Auxeſis uti ſcientiae maerorem intendit;<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.18.</note> Itidem (quoad <hi>voti modum</hi>) tunc anxiè dolebam Authorem ſuam ſiluiſſe Proſopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paeian, carum ſive inſtitutionem rerum ad quas verba ſic aptius conformart poſſent.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:121348:54"/>
            <p>Donec Doctiſſ. Hereis Effigiem libro ſuo praepoſitem contemplans obſervaram. Ut <hi>Album</hi> in manu tenens, ſub libri titulo, in Paginâ dextrâ haec bina verba quaſi ſcripſerat <hi>[mundus mens]</hi> In ſiniſtrâ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> quì ſedac vel addens <hi>[connubio jungam ſtabili.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quod annuere mihi videbatur ad divini Platonis in Tymaeo comparationem animae boninis cum Triangulo, in cujus apice ſit unitas; Ex uno latere ſe dilatans in numeros pares, <hi>2.4.8.</hi> Ex altero in impares, <hi>3.9.27.</hi> Pares numeri (ut notat<note n="*" place="margin">In Tym.</note> Proclus) corruptibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, ut &amp; impares aeternitatem demonſtrantes. Erin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> perpendens <hi>Naturam</hi> &amp; <hi>Rationem,</hi> quoad <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turantem,</hi> idem eſſe [quod &amp; ſacra<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 1.1.</note> Pagina pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat] ideòque ad Trianguli apicem apprimè compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem: à quo dein ut natura in mundum deſcendens di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viditur in Intellectualem &amp; viſibilem. Viſibilis ſuo modo Intelleitualem atteſtans. Sicque Ratio in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem prolapſa ut in cogitativam &amp; loquutoriam parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; [idam enim docet <hi>Ariſtoteles</hi> in libro de Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret. Ubiverba eſſe Cogitationum imagines perhibet] Putabam analogian adeo facilem; ac ſi libata [Ut Ulyſſen olim per Circen inſtructum feciſſe fertur] <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra dixiſſet.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Quod voves (Spectator) quam ad ineffabilia non pertinet, hum lori ſede quam Idaeis Platonicis acquieſcit. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde fit quod cum Ariſtotelicâ vel ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Hermeticâ Philoſophiâ [quae Platonicae corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rca eſt] aptius cohaeret. Quamsbrem ſicuti per <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotelis Materiam, Formam</hi> &amp; <hi>Privationem</hi> tota nobis patefit natura. Sic per verba <hi>Entitatis, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> &amp; <hi>Qualitatis</hi> abſolvitur loqucla; quum ceterae partes Orationis vel in ea ſunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>educibiles, aut ut ſatellites illis adſtant. Unicè ſaltem requiritur alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio haec: quòd ſcil. (quum <hi>Qualitas</hi> ut objectum ſupponit Perfectionem: ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> perceptibilis non ſit uiſi verbo Entitatis adjuncta, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t indelligibiliter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerta)
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121348:55"/>formetur ejus analogiae ad formam formatam ſive <hi>Proportionem.</hi> Quod enim <hi>Privatio</hi> in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectualibus, idem &amp; <hi>Proportio</hi> in corporeis quod ſit nullus non intelligit.</p>
               <p>Ob id verò, ut defectum, ſi ad Hermeticos te ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere mavis. Innumera corum volumina in Trinuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate hâc aſſentiri percipiás, viz. Ut <hi>Mercurius</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotechnic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Saturni</hi> ſcintillâ impregnatus, coquatur in <hi>Venerem</hi> quam cognominant <hi>Filiis notam.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Projectio (mi <hi>Praeſtantiſſimi)</hi> utcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Practicis vix ſuccedere videtur. Interim tamen ſi à ſpeoulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus quae ſub ſenſum cadunt ad eas quae intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ ſolâ percipiuntur aſcendamus, quid inde nobis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligendum erit aliud quàm <hi>Entitas</hi> movens ad <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionem.</hi> Ut (licèt liber ipſe vobiſcum vernaculari non mereatur) vel ex emblematibus cerni eſt.</p>
            <p>Et ſic <hi>mundus</hi> factus eſt. Inquit Hermes.<note place="margin">In Tab.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Quae mea igitur andacia eſt dum <hi>Mentem</hi> per trinuna illa verba communicativam reddere tento, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his ſubmittitur.</p>
            <p>R Reliquus liber horum examinat accidentia &amp; uſus; medum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, obiter, quo ceterae quas liberales vocamus artes ex illis pendent.</p>
            <p>De quibus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uper, dum apud familiares (inter po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula) pro hâc ratâ Sermocinabar: Eorum, ut Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſodemata iſta chartis darem,<note place="margin">Vos horter ut Scientia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Inſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umbatis. Et veterum labore; ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nihil, neque omnla eſſe putetis. Idem <hi>Verul.</hi> ad Acad. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </note> corrogationes abnuere nolui. Ni <hi>Verulamii</hi> noſtri hortamina (quae Doctiores nimium jam diu perpeſſos putaham) ex integro ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per neglecta maneant: aut (dum aegris adſtare non ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridet) Laurus, quam viginti nunc annis è vobis pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licè receptam ambio, radicitus mecum ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rileſccre vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deatur; omnigeno quaſi literarum uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> decſſet veſter</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ab eremo paterno in agro Glamorganiae Cambriae Calendis <date>
                     <hi>Martii.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Baſſertꝰ J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aneſius.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
